<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Division divided, or, Ruines fore-runner discovered and decyphered in a sermon before the right honourable and right worshipfull the Lord Major and Aldermen of the city of London, preached on the Lords-day, September 20, 1646, in Pauls Church, London / by one that wisheth well unto and daily prayeth for unity and uniformity in these three kingdomes.</title>
            <author>Bridges, Walter.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1646</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 171 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 36 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A29386</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B4484</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R23810</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">07911822</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 07911822</idno>
            <idno type="VID">40364</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A29386)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 40364)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1198:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Division divided, or, Ruines fore-runner discovered and decyphered in a sermon before the right honourable and right worshipfull the Lord Major and Aldermen of the city of London, preached on the Lords-day, September 20, 1646, in Pauls Church, London / by one that wisheth well unto and daily prayeth for unity and uniformity in these three kingdomes.</title>
                  <author>Bridges, Walter.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[7], 62 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Andrew Crooke,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1646.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"The epistle dedicatory," signed: Walter Bridges.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Matthew XII, 25 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:40364:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:40364:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>DI<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ISION DIVIDED;</hi> OR, Ruines fore-runner DISCOVERED and DECYPHERED, In a Sermon before the Right Honourable and the Right Worſhipfull the Lord Major and Aldermen of the City of <hi>London,</hi> Preached on the Lords-day, <hi>September</hi> 20. 1646. in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church, <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By one that wiſheth well unto, and daily prayeth for Unity and Uniformity in theſe three Kingdomes.</p>
            <q>
               <p>Now I beſeech you Brethren, by the Name of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, that yee all ſpeake one thing, and that there bee no diſſentions among you; but bee yee knit together in one minde, and in one judgement,
<bibl>
                     <hi>1 Cor. 1.10.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
               <p>Infaelix populus Dei non poteſt in bono tantam habere concordiam, quantam mali habent in malo,
<bibl>
                     <hi>Hier. in Pſ.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
               <p>Ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> enim Civitas in ſeditione poteſt eſſe beata, nec in diſcordia dominorum domus, qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> minus animus a ſeipſo diſſidens, ſecum<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> diſcordans, guſtare partem ullam liquidae voluptatis, &amp; liberae po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſt. At<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> pugnantibus &amp; contrariis ſtudiis, conſiliiſque ſemper utens nihil quiete videre, nihil tranquille poteſt,
<bibl>
                     <hi>Cicero.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,
<bibl>
                     <hi>Homer. Odyſſ. <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Andrew Crooke,</hi> at the <hi>Green Dragon</hi> in <hi>Pauls-church-yard,</hi> 1646.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:40364:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:40364:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE, A True patterne of the old and good Way of Pietie and Charity, and a cordiall Patron of Truth in theſe unſteady and giddy Times, <hi>THOMAS ADAMS,</hi> NOW Lord Major of this famous City of <hi>London,</hi> all bleſt eſtabliſhments in all the wayes to Grace and Glory.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Ou have made that ſaying true, which heretofore was ſpoken, <hi>Amicus Plato,</hi> and <hi>Amicus Socrates,</hi> but <hi>amiciſſima Veritas;</hi> I love <hi>Plato</hi> wel, and <hi>Socrates</hi> too, but Truth better than either of them; yea, than
<pb facs="tcp:40364:3"/>both of them. The hearts of Gods people bleſſe you, and God for you, and we hope your zeale for Truth againſt every oppoſite Error, ſhall ſtill provoke ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Confeſ. lib.</hi> 12.</note> 
               <hi>Veritatem celare, eſt aurum ſepelire,</hi> To conceale Truth, is as to bury gold, ſaith <hi>Auſtin:</hi> And <hi>Bernard</hi> convincingly, <hi>Si propter timorem mortis tacere Veritatem impietas eſt, quomodo non eſt major impietas, propter miſerum ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trem &amp; honoris vani ſpem tacere Veritatem? Videtur meliorem facere gratiam panis &amp; ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noris,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bernard.</note> 
               <hi>quam gloriam Veritatis;</hi> If for the feare of death to conceale a Truth be ſin and wickedneſſe; ô what a ſin is it, for the bellies-ſake, or ſome ſuch ſinister end to diſſemble it?
<note place="margin">Truth in 1 <hi>Petition.</hi> 2 <hi>Preſence.</hi> 3 <hi>Poſſeſſion.</hi>
               </note> My Lord, <hi>Inquiſitio Veritatis eſt ejus petitio, ſcientia Veritatis eſt ejus praeſentia, ſed creditio Veritatis eſt ejus poſſeſſio;</hi> Truth when ſought after is excellent, when found and knowne it is yet more lovely, but when beleeved and practiſed too, it becomes ours in poſſeſſion.
<note place="margin">Faith, what?</note> And indeed, what is Faith, but I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve? that is, I underſtand and conceive of it for a truth, I aſſent unto it in my Judgement to bee a truth, I conſent unto it in my will as good, and build mine eternall comfort on it as good for mee; this act of beliefe carries the whole ſoule with it. It is pleaſant to ſtand upon the ſhore, and ſee the Ships
<pb facs="tcp:40364:3"/>toſſed in the troubled Ocean; to stand upon a Caſtle ſafe, and ſee a pitch'd Battaile fought, in the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety and ſucceſſe thereof; to ſtand upon a rock and ſee (ſo it bee with pity, and without pride) the Errors, wandrings, miſts, clouds, and ſtormes, which are below in the valley of this world. Your Lordſhip hath like a ſtable Chriſtian ſtood faſt in God, and in the power of his might, while you have ſeen many (too many) toſſed to and fro with the wind of every Doctrine. Doubtleſſe, every godly,
<note place="margin">Movet mens pia in charitate, quieſcit in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>videntia, non vertit denique niſi ſuper pol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s veritatis.</note> truly godly mind moves in charity, rests in provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, and doth not turne, but upon the poles of Truth, while the portion of wicked men will bee; that they deceive, and are deceived. Mixtures of falſhood,
<note place="margin">Simile.</note> I may fitly reſemble them to that allay which is in gold, ſilver, or pewter, it may indeed make the met all worke ſomewhat the better, but it abaſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th it much; even ſo our notionall mixtures may indeed in preaching, preſſe, &amp;c. make things take the better among giddy heads, but they abaſe Divinity, and render men delighting therein too full of levity and emptineſſe.
<note place="margin">Gods attire if hee did dwell among men.</note> It was wont to bee ſaid of our Learned Criticks, That if God himſelf were to dwell in humane ſhape amongst men, hee would take light for his body, and truth for his ſoul.</p>
            <p>This City hath been exceedingly honoured in ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb facs="tcp:40364:4"/>out Champions to fight for Truth abroad, wherein with what gallantry and ſucceſſe our <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doners</hi> have behaved themſelves, Chronicles will not conceale in after times, and there are yet private Anniverſaries of thankefull remembrances for <hi>Newbery,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The 20 of <hi>Sep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tember,</hi> that day this Sermon was Preached.</note> 
               <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And it will bee no little Fame to this City alſo, to have it recorded, that in the time of ſuch a one, and ſuch a one ſeverall Lord Majors of <hi>London</hi> ſucceſſively, Hereſies, Schiſmes, Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctaries were ſuppreſſed, or at leaſt not ſo countenan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, as that the tares overgrew the wheate in Gods Field;
<note place="margin">Salvian.</note> 
               <hi>Dum mali eſſe volunt, Verita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem eſſe nolunt, qua mali condemnantur;</hi> but let Truth prevaile, and let it be glorious. Of all pieces of our Spirituall armour, Truth is reſembled unto a girdle, <hi>Epheſ. 6.</hi> for indeed, Truth ſhould incompaſſe us about;
<note place="margin">Truth foure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold.</note> And a fourfold Truth, <hi>ſcil.</hi> of judgment, heart, ſpeech, action, is required of eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Chriſtian. My Lord, the Lord of Lords take a double portion of the Spirit of <hi>Paul,</hi> and put it on you, and on all them that ſhall ſucceed you, that you may withſtand them to the face, which goe not with a right foot unto the Goſpel of Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>Non bene vivitur,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Holy life, what and how?</note> 
               <hi>ubi non bene de Deo credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, Aug.</hi> A holy life is indeed nothing elſe, but the infuſion of holy truths. The Spirit opening
<pb facs="tcp:40364:4"/>generall truths to a Chriſtian, hath another worke alſo, and that is to reveale our particular intereſt in thoſe truths, and to breed ſpeciall faith, whereby wee may make them our owne: that ſo where ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred truths are truly apprehended, there may be an impreſſion in the ſoule, ſuitable to the things be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved. The Lord make our believing of God Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty, to bread an impreſsion of dependence, reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, &amp;c.
<note place="margin">Some diſpute of Faith, ſome preach it, ſome ſweare by it, but few live thereby.</note> the belief and knowledge of Christ cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified, to bee a crucifying knowledge; of Chriſt ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, a raiſing knowledge; of Chriſt abaſed, an aba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing knowledge to our ſoules, and ſo of all truths elſe whatſoever. The good Prince <hi>George Anhalt,</hi> (who in <hi>Luthers</hi> time became a Preacher of the Goſpel) intending to comfort his brother Prince <hi>John,</hi> raiſeth ſtrong conſolations for him from the last three Articles of the Creed, Remiſſion of ſinnes, reſurrection of the body,
<note place="margin">Comfort in trouble, what and how?</note> and life everlaſting. There is one Article before theſe three, and that is the Communion of Saints, which we beleeve too, but finde as little influence from in theſe our dayes, as from any truth that ever our Lord Chriſt left us; and reaſon I know none thereof, but that there is ſo much of that knowledge which puffeth up, and ſo little of that love that edifieth. Hee that ſtrives for Error ſtrives for Satan againſt
<pb facs="tcp:40364:5"/>God,
<note place="margin">A holy ſtriſe.</note> he that ſtrives for victory, ſtrives for himſelf againſt other men; but hee that ſtrives for truth against errour, helps the Lord againſt Gods enemy and his too, namely, Satan the Father of lies. And this ſpecially,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bonum, benè,</hi> God loves Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verbes better than Adjectives</note> if withall hee handle Gods cauſe according unto God; A man ſhews moſt knowledge and underſtanding in the matter of truth, but moſt grace in the manner of handling of it with reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, holineſſe, and modeſty.</p>
            <p>Your Lordſhip hath ſo behaved your ſelf in your Yeare, that I doubt not but it will turne to your accompt before God, and amongst us your Name ſhall be as an Oyntment poured forth: Jeſus Chriſt bleſse you more and more with ſin's decreaſes, and graces increaſes, that you may bee perfect and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire, wanting nothing; So prayeth</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Lordſhips that loves you for loving Truth, Walter Bridges.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:40364:5"/>
            <head>TO THE FOVRE ESQVIRES FOR THE Service of this Honourable CITY, <hi>William Gunthrop</hi> Sword-bearer, <hi>John Clut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> Common-Hunt, <hi>Henry Hodges</hi> Common-Cryer, <hi>Edward Peerſe</hi> Water-bayliffe, Grace and Peace, with light and truth in the Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Our laſt Lord and Maſter Gentlemen, (O many ſuch more may you ſerve in that place) and you, are not ſuch men as ſome are; there is a rule among the <hi>Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts,</hi> and it is this, Wee are bound to the obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of the Pope, when hee ordaines a Holy Day, but wee are not bound to doe againſt our conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; How ſhall this now bee reconciled? For the Pope may happily command that which I cannot in conſcience doe: The <hi>Roman</hi> Doctors reconcile it eaſily, and it is thus, Make the word and will of
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:40364:6"/>the Pope, the rule of your obedience, and then it is enough; O ſlavery of all ſlaveries for any poore ſoule to lye under! Your Lord, and you love in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>largements, not to take any thing upon truſt, which doth concern your ſouls for eternity: but to bee perſwaded in your owne mindes, and to have your ſenſes exerciſed to diſcerne good and evil, your Lord, and you together, made it your requeſts that this poore word of exhortation might paſſe from the Pulpit to the Preſſe, it hath done ſo now, through the good hand of God, and here you have it, if it helpe you in any thing, one good turne de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves another, do you helpe him with your prayers, who is</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your loving Friend and Servant in ſuch workes as theſe, WALTER BRIDGES.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:40364:6"/>
            <head>
               <hi>DI<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ISION DI<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>IDED;</hi> OR, RVINES FORE-RVNNER Diſcovered and Diſciphered.</head>
            <head type="sub">The TEXT, <hi>Every Kingdome divided againſt it ſelf ſhall be brought to deſolation; and every City or houſe divided againſt it ſelf ſhall not ſtand,</hi> Mat. 12.25.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His is ſuch a piece of Gods truth, as being ſpoken by Chriſt himſelfe, ought much to be regarded, the occaſion thereof very eaſily gathered out of the Context; and as to that, or to the Text, with reference to the Context, I ſhall have no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to ſay, I ſhall looke on the Text with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference to our times rather, and labour to hold forth therehence unto this Honorable and grave Aſſembly ſuch truth as is Land, Church, and Common-wealth concerning: <hi>Calvin</hi>'s note is excellent and too true, Right Honourable and wel-beloved,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſt kic Divini verbi quaſi qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam genius, ut nunquam emer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gat quieto et dormiente Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tana;</hi> Cal. Praeſ. <hi>ad Reg.</hi> Gall.</note> that though while men ſlept, the envious man tooke his time to ſow tares, yet men never can take a time to wake and watch to preach truth while Satan is aſleep. <hi>Origen</hi> once being to preach on that place of the Pſalmiſt, <hi>Vnto the wicked God ſaith, What haſt thou to do to take my Name into thy mouth, &amp;c. ſeeing thou hateſt to be reformed;</hi> wept over the Text in ſtead of Preaching upon it. It is <hi>Pareus</hi> his obſervation upon that of the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.10. <hi>Now I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:40364:7"/>you brethren, by the Name of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, that yee all ſpeake the ſame thing, and that there bee no diviſions among you; but that yee bee perfectly joyned together in the ſame minde, and in the ſame judgement. Pareus,</hi> I ſay, marks, that the Apoſtle being to cure diviſion<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Huic morbo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ulceratiſſimo primum malag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mata quaedam adhibet.</hi> Par. ad loc.</note> to this diſeaſe, ſaith hee, <hi>Paul</hi> firſt applyes Play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters and Poulteſſes to ripen it, and draw it to maturation, before hee cut or make inciſion: our diſunions, disjoyntings, diſaffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions and diſſenſions are very great, very unreaſonable, very un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſonable, tongue-diſagreement, and pen-diſagreement; I yet hope God will keep us from diſcord, for that ſounds harſh, and is not till hearts bee broken aſunder, from which God deliver us. I would not have that ſaid of Chriſtians, which had wont to bee ſaid of Chronologers,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Chronologi non magis congruunt quam Horologia;</hi> Victorin. Stri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel. Proleg. in Chron. Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancth.</note> the Chronologers agree like clocks, ſcarce two of one minde throughout. It would bee our advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the eyes of God and good men to advance unity and one-mindedneſſe, leſt it bee ſaid of us, and truly too, that <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mades</hi> the Oratour ſaid of the <hi>Athenians</hi> in <hi>Plutarch,</hi> that they never ſate upon Treaties of Peace, but in black and mourning garments, when they had paid before too deare for their diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: <hi>Vis unita fortior,</hi> hath hitherto gone for a good Proverbe, and indeed if wee have a fancy of croſſing ſuch Proverbes, it may prove to our ruine. God, becauſe he is <hi>Ens ſimpliciſſimum,</hi> a moſt ſimple and undivided being, is therefore <hi>Ens fortiſſimum &amp; inexpugnabile,</hi> a moſt ſtrong and impregnable being; and ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, if wee hold together amongſt our ſelves, it will bee more hard to harme us: what is the deſtruction of a man, but the diviſion of the body and the ſoule? as long as they two hold together, the man is not deſtroyed; ſo is it alſo, and will bee found to bee amongſt us. Beſides that glorious light ſhining forth of Gods Word, whereunto they doe well that take heed as to a light ſhining in a darke place, ſuch as that, <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.17. <hi>I beſeech you brethren marke them which cauſe diviſion</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>:) and that 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.3. <hi>For yee are yet carnall; for whereas there are among you envyings, and ſtrife, and diviſions; are yee not carnall, and walk as men?</hi> Beſides theſe, &amp; ſuch as theſe Scriptures, the very light of nature, and men guided by no better Principles, will riſe up in judgement againſt men that call themſelves Chriſtians, and yet love diviſions. <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> in his fift Booke of a Common-wealth,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:40364:7"/>and ſixt Chapter, layes down this as an infallible rule, <hi>Imbellum eſt quod diſcordat,</hi> that which diſagrees with it ſelfe,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Ariſt. de Rep. l</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 6.</note> and is diſconcor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant, muſt needs be weake.</p>
            <p>But I come to the Text, wherein I obſerve:</p>
            <p>Firſt, the ſubject here ſpoken of, and that is, a Kingdome, a City, an houſe; a threefold ſubject is here ſpoken of.</p>
            <p>Secondly, the adjunct which ſerves to expreſſe our Lords meaning, and the Doctrines concernment, which is (every) Kingdome, City, Houſe, it is true in all that our Lord ſaith of any.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, the predicate, or that which is ſpoken of every of theſe ſubjects; which is both,
<list>
                  <item>1. Affirmative, ſhall be brought to deſolation.</item>
                  <item>2. Negative alſo, ſhall not ſtand.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, the condition annexed, if divided againſt it ſelf; Every King ſome divided againſt it ſelfe ſhall bee deſolate, and every City or Houſe divided againſt it ſelfe ſhall not ſtand. Then I come to the firſt part of the expoſition.</p>
            <p>Firſt, for the concernment of this Doctrine,
<note place="margin">1 The con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernment.</note> it belongeth it ſeemes unto our Kingdome in generall, unto our City in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, yea, and unto our very houſes, our habitations where wee live; a Doctrine doubtleſſe well-beſitting the eares of ſuch an Honourable, ſuch a Worſhipfull Auditory.
<note place="margin">Quintilian.</note> 
               <hi>Modus orationis Auditor est,</hi> was wont to bee the old rule, ſpeake to thy hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers profit, or ſay nothing. If men are not <hi>pro ara diminica,</hi> yet their <hi>hara domeſtica</hi> I know will move them, the Kingdom, your City, your Houſes, all is here concerned.
<note place="margin">Lutherus me al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loquitur quaſi me intra erat.</note> It had wont to bee ſaid of <hi>Luther,</hi> that hee ſpake to his hearers as if he had been within them: I ſhall not ſtudy ourious words, a conſciencious diſcovery, yea, a cordiall reproofe is farre better; and I am of <hi>Chryſoſtomes</hi> minde, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, new wayes are no wayes. When <hi>Ariſtippus</hi> was asked, what it would profit ones ſonne if his Father ſhould give him Learning; why (ſaith hee) if for nothing elſe, yet herein it will advantage him, that when hee comes to the Theater, hee ſhall ſit not like one ſtone upon another. If this Doctrine will ſerve for nothing elſe, yet this it will ſerve for to warne you yee Senators of <hi>London,</hi> that yee be not ſuch of whom mine Author ſayes, they had rather periſh
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:40364:8"/>in a common calamity,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pateroulus. ut Publica ruina quiſque malit, quam ſua pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teri, et idem paſſurus minime conſpici.</hi> 2 The Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection.</note> then in a private miſery, that their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction may be hidden in the publique ruine.</p>
            <p>Secondly, If any lazie objection ſhall bee awakened here from negligent ones, and thoſe which are ſecure, of which ſort we have our thouſands, and ten thouſands in this City: If any ſuch ſhall ſay unto me, what is this to mee? I doe not trouble mine head with your diviſions, preach mee Jeſus Chriſt, I take no care for any thing elſe. I Anſwer.</p>
            <p>The men of <hi>Laiſh</hi> that lived ſecurely are riſen againe in our times:
<note place="margin">Rev. 18.7, 8.</note> It was <hi>Babylons</hi> voyce, <hi>Rev.</hi> 18.7, 8. <hi>I ſit as a queene, and am no widow, I ſhall ſee no mourning;</hi> and ſhee ſpeakes this ſo loud and ſo long, till at length in the next verſe God ſayes to her,
<note place="margin">As is the Preacher, ſo is the peace al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes.</note> 
               <hi>Therefore ſhall her plagues come in one day, death and ſorrow, &amp;c.</hi> Therefore, wherefore? as is the peace, ſo alwayes is the Preacher thereof, when they ſay peace, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.3. When who ſayes ſo? wicked men, when they Preach a wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed peace, the juſt God even then holds himſelfe ingaged to bee againſt both the Peace, and Preacher, <hi>And your Covenant with death ſhall bee diſanulled and your agreement with Hell ſhall not ſtand, when a ſcourge ſhall run over and paſſe through the Land, then ſhall yee bee trod downe thereby,</hi> Eſa. 28.18.</p>
            <p>That word of <hi>Paul</hi> comes like thunder from Heaven, and it is ſuch language, as I deſire to ſpeake to ſuch men: Boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifulneſſe towards thee if thou continue in Gods bountiful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, or elſe even thou alſo ſhall be cut off, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.22.</p>
            <p>I would have the Citizens of <hi>London</hi> doe, as the Citizens of <hi>Nineveh</hi> did at ſuch a meſſage, <hi>Jonah</hi> 3.6. When the King, and Nobles,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c.</note> and others, ſaw the word of God, (not heard it onely, for ſo the Originall expreſſeth it, <hi>Luke</hi> 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>15) ſee the gradation, or rather the deſcenſion, yea, condeſcenſion, 1. The word came (like lightning.) 2. To the King, not to the inferior onely. 3. Hee aroſe, as if hee felt his ſeat ſhake un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der him. 4. Caſt off his Robe, as if it had beene a burthen. 5. Covered himſelfe with Sackcloth, as a corps made ready for the burial 6. And ſate down, not among violets, flowers, &amp;c. but in the aſhes: the word of God if it have power to worke repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, that repentance will have power to worke pardon at laſt.</p>
            <p>But thirdly,
<note place="margin">3 The Obligat.</note> What obligation find you in the Text to tye us to all this?</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:40364:8"/> 1. The leſſer obligation, the Kingdome, City,
<note place="margin">1 Leſſer.</note> or houſe ſo divided, ſhall not ſtand: when Iſrael could not ſtand before her enemies, <hi>Joſh.</hi> 7.8. that Governour preſently breakes out into this expreſſion, <hi>O Lord, what ſhall I ſay when Iſrael turne their backs before their enemies?</hi> The Kingdome, City, or houſe divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded ſhall not ſtand, they ſhall bee as <hi>Ireland;</hi> let our Governours then doe as hee did.</p>
            <p n="2">2. But then the greater, they ſhall bee deſolate, bee as <hi>Germany,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Greater.</note> where there hath been neither earing nor ſeed-time this Twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty yeares and upwards, for body nor for ſoule. When Chriſt foretells the ruine of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> it is in ſuch termes as theſe, <hi>Verily, I ſay unto you, there ſhall not bee here left a ſtone upon a ſtone which ſhall not bee caſt downe, Mat.</hi> 24.2. ſuch, ſuch a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation it will be, that followes diviſion hard at heeles.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, then marke that (<hi>if</hi>) in my Text,
<note place="margin">4 The Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> If it bee divided, if it, if another thing, if any thing, if thou bee divided againſt thy ſelfe, thou ſhalt not ſtand, thou ſhalt bee brought to deſolation, <hi>For a double-minded man is unſtable in all his wayes, I am.</hi> 1.8. Now this I would have inlarged and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Implicitly, if a Kingdome, City,
<note place="margin">1 Implicitly.</note> or houſe bee divided a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt others, there may bee miſery enough, the ſword will ſoone pierce unto the heart, <hi>Jerem.</hi> 4.10. <hi>Then the horſeman lifteth the bright ſword, and the glittering ſpeare, a multitude is ſlaine; yea, the dead bodies are many, and they ſtumble at their corpſes, Nahum</hi> 3.3. <hi>England</hi> can now tell, and <hi>Ireland</hi> too ſad ſtories, and then wee were divided againſt others onely, againſt men, which though they were amongſt us, were not of us. But</p>
            <p n="2">2. Explicitely, if divided againſt it ſelfe:
<note place="margin">2. Explicitly.</note> Divines uſe to ſay there is one word in a Text which is alwayes to bee marked: This ſame word (<hi>ſelfe</hi>) The Kingdome divided againſt it ſelfe, the City and the houſe againſt it ſelf, occaſions us to inquire fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for a further expoſition, and to make ſearch into the ſecond part of this expoſition.</p>
            <p n="1">1. What is the Self of a Kingdome, City, houſe, Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, or perſon? To which I anſwer:</p>
            <p>Firſt, generally, thus, by <hi>Deut.</hi> 4.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, 6. <hi>Behold I have taught
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:40364:9"/>you Ordinances and Lawes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Selfe, what<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 1 Generally.</note> 
               <hi>as the Lord my God commanded mee, that yee ſhould doe even ſo, within the Land whither yee goe to poſſeſſe it: Keepe them therefore, and doe them, for that is your wiſdome and your underſtanding, &amp;c.</hi> Or by that of <hi>Solomon, Eccleſ.</hi> 12.13. <hi>Feare God, and keepe his Commandenients.</hi> For <hi>hoc eſt totum hominis,</hi> this is the ſelfe, the ſoule, the all of man: and what Kingdom, City, or houſe ſoever is divided againſt this, is divided againſt it ſelf, and will bee deſolate.</p>
            <p>Secondly,
<note place="margin">2 Particularly. 1 Kingdom ſelf.</note> but particularly: 1. The Selfe of a Kingdome, is the Religion of that Kingdome, from which whoſoever is divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, he is ſeparate from God, and God from him; and God will make him to know (at one time or other) that there is a God whom hee hath not ſerved. At the beginning of their dwelling there, they ſerved not God; therefore the Lord ſent Lyons amongſt them, which ſlew them, ſaith the Hiſtory, 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 17.25. <hi>If my people, which is called by my name, hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble themſelves, and pray, and ſeeke my face, and turne from their wicked wayes, then I will forgive their ſinnes, and will heale their Land.</hi> Religion you ſee is the onely miſery-diverting, and mercy-procuring thing in a Land or Nation.</p>
            <p>Secondly,
<note place="margin">2 Common-wealth ſelf.</note> the Selfe of a Common-wealth, is the Law thereof, the Law is the common Surety betweene the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours, and the governed, ſurety from the King to mee, that I ſhall enjoy my protection, and ſurety for mee to him, that I ſhall pay my tribute,
<note place="margin">No<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>heire of reſtraint.</note> and doe mine homage. Over and over againe in that Hiſtory it is recorded, <hi>In thoſe dayes there was no [King] in Iſrael, and every man did that which was right in his owne eyes, Judg.</hi> 20.25. Now a Kingdome or Common-wealth divided againſt this Selfe alſo, will bee deſolate.</p>
            <p>Thirdly,
<note place="margin">3 Church ſelf.</note> the ſelfe of the Church is Doctrine and Diſcipline, which like the body and ſoule muſt not bee divided; <hi>Remember Jeſus Chriſt of the ſeed of</hi> David, <hi>how hee was crucified according to my Goſpel,</hi> 2 Tim. 2.8. <hi>This is that foundation other than which no man can lay,</hi> 1 Cor. 3.11. the doctrine of the Prophets and Apoſtles whereon wee muſt be built, whilſt Ieſus Chriſt himſelfe is laid for the cheif corner Stone. This Ieſus Chriſt who made a whip of cords, and drave out the buyers and ſellers out of the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:40364:9"/>Temple, which was a peece of Diſcipline, while hee was preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing heavenly doctrine to them, gave alſo the keyes unto <hi>Peter, Mat.</hi> 16. and <hi>Paul</hi> puts the power of them in execution. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.45. and writeth to the <hi>Coloſſians</hi> thus, <hi>Though I bee abſent in the body, yet am I with you in the Spirit, joying and beholding your order, and your ſtedfaſt faith in Chriſt, Col.</hi> 2.5.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The ſelf of a family is the Peace of that family, Peace I ſay,
<note place="margin">4 Family ſelf.</note> the Religious peace, while the family is reconciled to God, for then they know that peace is upon their Tabernacle, that is, they are aſſured thereof, then they viſite their Habitation and doe not ſinne, <hi>Iob.</hi> 5.24. and the mutuall peace betweene the ſeverall members thereof maintained by commanding and obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, the man dwels with his wife and family like a man of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.7. the wife alſo knowes that ſhe is not permitted to teach, nor to uſurpe authority over the man, but to bee in ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.12. this is a ſelfe againſt which it will be found ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry dangerous to be divided.</p>
            <p n="5">5. There is a ſelfe of a mans ſelfe,
<note place="margin">5 Self of ſelſe.</note> and that is good conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; good I ſay, tender, and wel-informed conſcience, not accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing when it ſhould excuſe; nor on the contrary excuſing, when groſſe faults are committed: Conſcience perſwaded of the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility and neceſſity too of Religion:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Quas non oper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tet mortes praec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligere, quod non ſuppliciwn po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius ferre? imo in quam profun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam inferni a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byſſum introire, quam contra conſerentiam atteſtari?</hi> Zuing. Epiſt. 3.</note> ſuch a Conſcience as the godly Miniſter writes of, ſaying, O what deaths would not a man firſt chooſe? what puniſhment would not a man (a godly man) undergoe, even the very bottome of hell it ſelf, before he would doe any thing againſt conſcience?</p>
            <p>I proceed to the further expoſition, the third Part thereof.</p>
            <p>Shall they be brought to deſolation indeed if divided? is our Lord in good earneſt? and ſhall this come to paſſe?</p>
            <p>I anſwer, the meaning is, 1. So it happens to be probably and very often.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Yea, and more than ſo, ſo it will be certainly,
<note place="margin">3 Part of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition.</note> and without all doubt, unleſſe ſuch diviſions as have been, or are in Kingdom, City, or houſe be confeſſed, repented of and forſaken; For ſo are the two ſtanding rules which God gives, one is <hi>Jerem.</hi> 18.7, 8.
<note place="margin">2 Rules.</note> 
               <hi>At what inſtant I ſhall ſpeake concerning a Nation, and concerning a Kingdom, to pluck up and to pull down, and to deſtroy it, If that Nation against whom I have pronounced, turn from their evill, I will repent of the evill that I thought to doe unto them.</hi> The other is <hi>Prov.</hi> 28.13. <hi>Hee
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:40364:10"/>that hideth his ſinne ſhall not proſper, but hee that confeſſeth and forſaketh ſhall have mercy.</hi> If our diviſions continue in Kingdome, City, Houſe, they be of ſad preſage, what ever men thinke.</p>
            <p>Here now with reference to the Text and Context, let mee conclude ſomething doctrinally by way of obſervation.</p>
            <p>Firſt,
<note place="margin">Obſervations.</note> A Kingdome divided amongſt themſelves, againſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, is worſe in that regard than the Devils Kingdome, Satans Kingdome is not ſo.</p>
            <p>Secondly, The Favorers and Fomenters of ſuch diſcord are, ſhall I ſay Devils? or worſe? the Fiends ſeeke the peace of their owne kingdome.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, The Devils doe agree, that they may doe evill, but wee cannot agree that wee may doe good, and receive good too, namely that we may ſettle peace &amp; truth in our borders, and when wee have done, ſit downe and eat the fruit thereof. <hi>Suidas</hi> writes that there was a family at <hi>Corinth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ventiſopii</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> that could lay the winds, and that that family was in very great eſteeme among all, but eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially the ſea men, &amp; had therefore a name given them, <hi>Ventiſopii:</hi> That ſtorme of ſad diviſion hanging over our heads, His hand ſurely muſt be in the calming thereof, of whom it was ſaid, <hi>that both the winde and waters did obey him,</hi> Mat. 8.27.</p>
            <p>But I proceed,
<note place="margin">4 Part of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, what?</note> and aske againe in the fourth part of the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition.</p>
            <p>Whether the diviſions of a Kingdome, City or houſe bee all alike, or all alike dangerous, and preſaging ruine? No ſurely.</p>
            <p>Firſt,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Diviſion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſelf.</note> of Kingdom diviſion, you may read the Hiſtory of <hi>Reho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boam,</hi> 1 <hi>King.</hi> 12. and of the rending away of 10. Tribes of 12 from him? Here now is the ruine, but was this Kingdome divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded againſt it ſelfe? O yes, for it was divided againſt counſell, and Counſell is the very ſelfe of a King and Kingdome too, <hi>v.</hi> 14. it is ſaid, <hi>that the King ſpake unto them after the counſell of the young Men ſaying, My Father made your yoke heavy, and I will adde to your yoke: My father alſo chaſtiſed you with whips, but I will chaſtiſe you with ſcorpions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Diviſion.</note> For a City diviſion, you may read that Hiſtory, <hi>Acts</hi> 14.4. <hi>But the multitude of the City was divided, and part held with the Jews, and part with the Apoſtles.</hi> Here now is a City diviſion, you ſee part ſiding againſt part, and tending (as all diviſions doe) to tumult and trouble, for <hi>v.</hi> 5. <hi>There was an aſſault made both of the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:40364:10"/>Gentiles and alſo of the Jews with their rulers, to uſe them deſpightfully, and to ſtone them, they were ware of it, and faine to fly to</hi> Lyſtra <hi>and to</hi> Derbe; But were theſe alſo divided againſt themſelves? yes ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, they were divided againſt Religion Preached, and wiſedome to judge thereof. To diſcerne things that differ, is that which <hi>Pauls</hi> prayer is for, <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.10.
<note place="margin">Sapientia cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitur in Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paratis.</note> and this wiſedome is beſt diſcern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, when things are in competition, and the queſtion is, what to chooſe, and what to refuſe.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Of Houſe difference you may alſo read 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 6.16.
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Diviſion.</note> 20, 21. <hi>David</hi> a good husband, doing devoutly, and with much zeal before the Arke of the God of Iſrael, <hi>Michael</hi> his wife is of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother opinion, and ſhee lookes on and deſpiſeth him in her heart, <hi>v.</hi> 16, ſhee ſaith, <hi>How glorious was the King to day, who un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered himſelfe to day in the eyes of the Handmaids of his ſervants? v.</hi> 20. <hi>as one of the vaine fellows openly uncovereth himſelfe.</hi> Here you ſee is a Houſe badly divided, and againſt it ſelfe too: namely Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent and Submiſſion of the wife to the Husbands judgement, in the undertaking of things in Gods ſervice; ſeverall diviſions are doubtleſſe ſeverally ominous, and to be taken heed of, they bode ill.</p>
            <p>But yet fifthly in my expoſition, they, the people,
<note place="margin">5 Part of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition.</note> I meane the Jews, might take Jeſus Chriſt for an exorciſt, or Conjurer, and if ſo, Satan ſhould then bee againſt himſelfe; wee ſee among the Papiſts ſometimes what a worke they have in their diſpoſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings, and yet Satan doth but caſt out Satan, if the worke bee done: wee read alſo <hi>Act.</hi> 19.13. <hi>that certain of the vagabond Jewes exorciſts tooke upon them to call over them which had evill ſpirits, the Name of the Lord Jeſus, ſaying, Wee adjure you by Jeſus whom</hi> Paul <hi>preacheth.</hi> To omit much that might be ſaid to this particular, I ſay onely this:</p>
            <p n="1">1. Our Lord argues againſt his blaſphemers,
<note place="margin">1. <hi>Arg. Ab abſurdo.</hi>
               </note> here <hi>ab abſurdo</hi> from the abſurdity, thus a Kingdome, City, or Houſe to be divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded againſt it ſelfe is abſurd. If Satans ſhould ſo be, it would be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive thereto.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Our Saviour argues from example,
<note place="margin">2. <hi>Arg. Ab exemplo.</hi>
               </note> I caſt out Devils by the ſame power that your ſonnes, (which can ſo doe) caſt them out, but aske them and they'l tell you, that they caſt them out by the finger of God, therefore by that power I caſt them out.
<note place="margin">3. <hi>Arg. Ab officio.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Another Argument our Saviour drawes from his office,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:40364:11"/>as if hee ſhould ſay, you would hardly ſtumble at my ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting out Devills, did you but know this, that Jeſus Chriſt came to deſtroy the works of the Devill, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.8.</p>
            <p>Sixthly,
<note place="margin">6 Part of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition.</note> a cleare difference is here held forth, and ought to bee marked, betweene ſome differences and others: for the Text doth not ſay, that all differences in a Kingdome, Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, or Houſe are deſtructive and tending to deſolation, but ſuch as are againſt the ſelf. The Scripture gives us to underſtand that there are</p>
            <p n="1">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Diviſions. </seg>1</label> 1. Preventionall diviſions, ſuch as did ariſe out of care of the glory of God, and caution leſt Idolatry ſhould bee committed, or ſuch ſinne as might kindle the fire of Gods indignation, and make it burne in, yea, burne up the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation: Of ſuch a diviſion wee read, <hi>Joſh.</hi> 22.16. <hi>Thus ſaith the whole Congregation of the Lord, VVhat treſpaſſe is this that yee have committed againſt the God of Iſrael, to turne away this day from following the Lord, in that you have builded you an Altar that yee might rebell this day againſt the Lord?</hi> To be divided from them that ſeeme to divide from the Lord, is a good diviſion.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Diviſions. </seg>2</label> 2. There are preceptive diviſions too, diviſions by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement from the Lord; ſuch alſo wee reade of, <hi>Exod.</hi> 32.26, 27. <hi>Then</hi> Moſes <hi>ſtood in the gate of the Campe, and ſaid, Who is on the Lords ſide, let him come unto me: And all the ſonnes of Levi gathered themſelves together unto him. And hee ſaid unto them, Thus ſaith the Lord God of Iſrael, Put eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man his ſword by his ſide, and go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in and out from gate to gate, throughout the Campe, and ſlay every man his brother, and every man his companion,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Poenaemirabilis. Caie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>and every man his neighbour.</hi> Here is a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion you ſee, though bloody, yet bleſſed, a piece of Juſtice acceptably done upon the ring-leaders into Idolatry, one of Gods wonderfull puniſhments, as juſt as ſecret.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Diviſions. </seg>3</label> 3. There are providentiall diviſions, ſuch as though they ſeeme never ſo ſtrange unto the ſonnes of men, yet are guided by the counſell and providence of the moſt High, without whom Kingdomes are not rent and divided; ſo we read, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 12.15. <hi>The King hearkened not unto the people, for the cauſe was from the Lord, that he might performe his ſaying, which the Lord ſpake by</hi> Ahijah <hi>the</hi> Shilonite, <hi>unto</hi> Jeroboam <hi>the ſon of</hi> Nebat: and what word that was, you may ſee, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 11.11. <hi>Feraſmuch as this is done of thee,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:40364:11"/>and thou haſt not kept my Covenant and my Statutes which I have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded thee, I will ſurely rend the Kingdome from thee, and give it to thy ſervant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Diviſions. </seg>4</label> 4. Wee read of converſionall and convictionall diviſions, when the God of power makes his Word the power of God, quick and powerfull, and ſharper than any two-edged ſword, piercing even to the dividing aſunder of ſoule and ſpirit, and of the joints and marrow, and is a diſcerner of the thoughts and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents of the heart, <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.12.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Diviſions. </seg>5</label> 5. The Miniſters duty, is it not rightly to divide the word of truth? 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.15. Hee muſt divide the precious from the vile, <hi>Lev.</hi> 10.10. By all this then is plainly to bee ſeen, that there are diviſions which are good, and to be obſerved.</p>
            <p>Seventhly, then we are to underſtand,
<note place="margin">7 Part of the Expoſition.</note> that this is a proverbiall ſpeech that our Lord uſeth here, and how ſuch parables and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verbes are in holy Scripture uſed is worthy obſervation, they conclude probably, and convince notably, and to ſuch purpoſes are for the moſt part uſed, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 24.12, 13. <hi>The Lord judge be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene mee and thee, and the Lord avenge mee of thee, but mine hand ſhall not bee upon thee:</hi> As ſaith the Proverbe of the Ancients,
<note place="margin">Proverbes.</note> 
               <hi>Wickedneſſe proceedeth from the wicked, but mine hand ſhall not bee upon thee:</hi> ſee alſo 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 20.18. they were wont to ſpeake in old time, ſaying, They ſhall ſurely aske counſell at <hi>Abel,</hi> and ſo they ended the matter, or ſurely they will aske of <hi>Abel,</hi> and ſo make an end; it is a reference unto <hi>Deut.</hi> 20.10. <hi>When thou c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> unto a City to fight againſt it, then thou ſhalt proclaime peace unto it:</hi> and ſo the ſumme of the Womans ſpeech is this, I and my Citizens thought, ſurely this Generall <hi>Joab</hi> will make his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands known before he come with fire and ſword, but thou fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweſt no ſuch order; <hi>Joabs</hi> anſwer you ſee in <hi>v.</hi> 20. and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by you may ſee how concluding and convincing the womans lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage is, ſo is our Lords here.</p>
            <p>Eightly, this Text muſt alſo bee looked upon in the harmony,
<note place="margin">8 Part of the Expoſition.]</note> three Evangeliſts have it, <hi>Matthew, Mark,</hi> and <hi>Luke,</hi> out of all which the termes muſt be very carefully expounded in their ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall orders: As</p>
            <p n="1">1. Shall be deſolate. I would aske here what is deſolation?
<note place="margin">1 Deſolation, what?</note> and make anſwer to this queſtion by that place, <hi>Gen.</hi> 47.19. <hi>Wherefore ſhall wee die before thine eyes? &amp;c. give us ſeed that wee may
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:40364:12"/>live and not die, that the land bee not deſolate,</hi> that is, that the land be not untilled; an unhusbanded land is a deſolate land, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions in a Kingdome, City, or houſe will make them to bee un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>husbanded both in heavenly and earthly ſenſe.
<note place="margin">2 Not ſtanding</note> 2. Shall not ſtand. Standing in Scripture is taken diverſly, as to ſtand in grace, that is, to be certaine and ſure of grace, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.2. <hi>By whom wee have acceſſe by faith into this grace wherein wee ſtand, and rejoice in hope of the glory of God:</hi> This way diviſions in a Kingdome, City, or Houſe, make it and them they cannot ſtand, it is loving of one another, and watchfulneſſe over one another, that is to edificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> dividing againſt one another tends to deſtruction.</p>
            <p>Standing,
<note place="margin">Standing in the acceptions</note> in Scripture, meanes alſo ſtanding ſtill, that is to ſay, to be quiet and reſt on God, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 20.17. <hi>Yee ſhall not need to fight in this battaile, ſet your ſelves, ſtand yee ſtill, and ſee the ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Lord with you. O Judah and Jeruſalem;</hi> This way alſo diviſions in a Kingdome, City, or Houſe weaken much, for when men divide and ſide it one againſt another, they are turbulent, not waiting on God with meekneſſe of ſpirit.</p>
            <p>Standing againe in holy Scripture, noteth ſtanding faſt, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to going away or falling from ſomewhat, or being carryed away; ſo <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.1. <hi>Stand faſt in the liberty wherewith Chriſt hath made us free, and bee not intangled againe with the yoake of bondage.</hi> Thus diviſions in a Kingdome, City, or Houſe are dangerous alſo; for in theſe tongue and pen-diviſions, moſt of our people are ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther loſt and become Atheiſts, looking after no Religion at all, on elſe are become children toſſed to and fro, and carryed about with every wind of Doctrine, by the ſleight of men, and cunning craftineſſe, whereby they lye in wait to deceive; ſo ſaith the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.14.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Houſe falleth upon houſe,
<note place="margin">Houſe falling upon houſe.</note> 
               <hi>Luke</hi> 11.17. an excellent expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, I expound it by that of <hi>Jotham,</hi> Judg. 9.20. <hi>Let fire come out from Abimelech and devoure the men of Shechem and the houſe of Millo; And let fire come forth from the men of Shechem, and from the houſe of Millo, and devoure Abimelech.</hi> Diviſions make fire breake out of one houſe, and burn another, contention is a flame, diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion is a kindled fire. Not without cauſe is it that the Holy Ghoſt, reckoning up the fruits of the fleſh, places them thus in the cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue, ſeditions, hereſies, envyings, murthers, to teach us what diviſion will come to, if God doe not reſtrain it, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.20, 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:40364:12"/> 4. If Satan caſt out Satan, that is,
<note place="margin">Caſtings out of</note> if they bee againſt one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, which ſhould be together,
<note place="margin">1 The Houſe.</note> there will bee nothing but ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting out. And there is a threefold caſting out. 1. Caſting out of the houſe, ſo <hi>Abram</hi> caſt <hi>Hagar</hi> and her ſon; and 2 ep. <hi>Joh.</hi> 10. <hi>If there come any unto you, and bring not this doctrine, receive him not into your houſe, neither bid him God ſpeed.</hi> When diviſions ariſe, even they that were intimate before, then caſt one another off, and out too, and hardly bid God ſpeed, give a ſalute each to other.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Caſting out of the heart;
<note place="margin">2 The Heart</note> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to be obſerved, <hi>Jer.</hi> 15.1. <hi>Though Moſes and Samuel ſtood be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore mee, yet my minde could not bee toward this people, caſt them out of my ſight, and let them goe forth:</hi> When diviſions come, men, and good men too are caſt out of one anothers hearts, the minde of one is not toward another.</p>
            <p n="3">3. A third caſting out yet there is mentioned by St.
<note place="margin">3 The Society.</note> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>Titus</hi> 3.10. <hi>A man that is an Heretique, after the firſt and ſecond ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition reject;</hi> that ſame reject, is as bad as an eject. For it imports.</p>
            <p n="1">1. To caſt him out of all familiarity in things temporall.</p>
            <p n="2">2. And out of all ſociety in things ſpiritual alſo. And ſuch ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtings out are the effects of diviſions too, wee are divided about judging of Errors and Heretiques; and divided againe about the caſting out and taking into communion.</p>
            <p>I ſhall therefore now come to Uſe and direction, that all this may be made yours, Jeſus Chriſt bleſſing his owne Ordinance.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe. </seg>1</label> The firſt Uſe that I have to give in, it is an Uſe of Caution, of caution to take heed, ſuch a take heed befits this Auditory,
<note place="margin">Caution.</note> as is written, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 19.6, 7. <hi>Take heed what yee doe, for yee judge not for man, but for the Lord, who is with you in the matter of judgement. Wherefore now let the feare of the Lord bee upon you, and take heed, and doe it.</hi> But I have another take heed,
<note place="margin">Selfe, <hi>Englands</hi> abomination.</note> and ſuch a one as I am con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident will be welcome, and that is, take heed to your ſelves; yea, I beſeech you take heed that you doe not welcome this take heed under a wrong notion. I know there is an Idol called Selfe, ſet up in every corner almoſt, and men fall downe and worſhip it, great men, learned men, all ſorts. I am an enemy to this <hi>Dagon,</hi> and doe heartily wiſh that ſome <hi>Hezekiah</hi> may bee ſtirred up, or at leaſt much of that ſpirit to make it (a <hi>Nehuſhtan</hi> once) a piece of braſſe whenſoever abuſed to idolatry.</p>
            <p>Three kinds of ſelfe-denyall I conceive ought to bee found in
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:40364:13"/>every Chriſtian:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Abnegatio</hi> 1 <hi>Mediorum.</hi> 2 <hi>Morum.</hi> 3 <hi>Mentium.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>abnegatio,</hi> 1. <hi>Mediorum,</hi> the means allowed by others; a right Chriſtian will not uſe the meanes, lawfull enough, thereby to bring unlawfull purpoſes to paſſe.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Morum,</hi> ſelf-denyall in the manners allowed by others; what other men think may be ſpoken, done, &amp;c. he dare not, that is a right Chriſtian, meddle in.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Mentium,</hi> ſelf-denyall in the mind, the very mind which the men of the world have, the ſame minde is in them, which was alſo in Chriſt Ieſus, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.5. <hi>Who made himſelf of no reputation, but tooke upon him the forme of a ſervant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Such a ſweet temper of heart, ſuch an aptneſſe and readineſſe to deny and forſake what's moſt deare unto us for Ieſus Chriſt, and for his Goſpels ſake; this is it, 1. Whoſe voice ſpeakes thus to God and the world, I am ready to be bound and dye, <hi>Act.</hi> 21.13. I account all Things droſſe and dung, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.8. 2. The parts of ſelf-denyall are affection and action, readineſſe in habit, and readineſſe in act.
<note place="margin">Selves to bee heeded.</note> 3. The condition of things ſtand in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petition with God. 4. The caution thereof, which is, that neither affection be deſtroyed, nor obedience, &amp;c. but reduced into order, namely, that God bee firſt, and all things after him.</p>
            <p>But for the particulars:</p>
            <p>Firſt,
<note place="margin">1 Self myſticall</note> I would intreat your to looke unto your ſelfe myſticall; that is, I pray you looke to your Religion, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, God is the beſt of beings, and Religion the beſt of wel-beings. He that hath little zeale, and leſſe cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage for godlineſſe, may (in appearance) look after many Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions, but he will hardly love any. Nor doe I preſſe Religion onely here, no nor it reformed, though I daily pray that the worke of Reformation may finde as many helpes in the end, as it hath found hinderances in the beginning and mid-way. But I pray you take heed of your Religion under <hi>Eſay</hi>'s notion,
<note place="margin">Religion what in good earneſt</note> 
               <hi>One ſhall ſay, I am the Lords; and another ſhall call himſelfe by the name of Jacob; and another ſhall ſubſcribe with his hand unto the Lord, and ſurname himſelfe by the name of Iſrael, Eſa.</hi> 44.5. your ſubſcribed Religion with your hands lifted up to the moſt High: I preſſe Religion under <hi>Pauls</hi> notion, <hi>Acts</hi> 10.35. <hi>To feare God, and worke righteouſneſſe;</hi> and under the deſcription of St. <hi>James, Jam.</hi> 1.27. <hi>To viſit the fatherleſſe and widow in their affliction,</hi> piety and charity going hand in hand.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:40364:13"/> 1.
<note place="margin">1 <hi>In praxei.</hi>
               </note> In practiſe is <hi>ſacras Scriptures rectè legit qui vertit verba in opera,</hi> Expoſitors of Scripture in their bookes we have good ſtore, and welcome light, but the Lord increaſe the number of them which expound Scripture, not in leaves onely, but in lives alſo, turne words into workes.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In tryall, bring Religion to the touch-ſtone;
<note place="margin">2 <hi>In probation</hi>
               </note> betweene Heaven and Hell, there's this difference in Heaven, there's Light without Heat, but in Hell there's Heat without Light, take heed of ſuch religion.</p>
            <p n="3">3. In influence, as the Heavens worke upon our bodies,
<note place="margin">3 <hi>In influentia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi>
               </note> ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed ſhould Religion on our ſoules: with,
<list>
                  <item>1. <hi>Light.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Lucis.</note>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>Heat.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Caloris.</note>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. <hi>Motion.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Motus.</note>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>That is worthy of notice which one ſaid wittily: <hi>Reprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſio i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ipit à modeſtia cum minoritis, Reformatione vero à Majeſtate cum majoritis,</hi> Modeſty ſhewes it ſelfe well in the reprehenſion of the Minorites, but Majeſty ſhewes it ſelfe better in the reformation of the Majorites. I adde ſome Counſells:</p>
            <p n="1">1. He that will give God his due in Religion,
<note place="margin">Counſells.</note> muſt be excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding carefull to make him, 1. The object, and 2. The appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of our Worſhip; it is ſaid, <hi>Revel.</hi> 9.20. <hi>That they worſhipped Divels,</hi> not becauſe they ſerved them, but becauſe they followed their ſuggeſtions in the deviſed way of ſerving God.</p>
            <p n="2">2. An afflicted eſtate had need of Religion to ſuſtaine it, a proſperous ſtate to perfect it in the end, and to moderate in the way, becauſe therefore Religion is to God alone, and the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtation of it unto man; let men be 1. well grounded in it. 2. well reſolved of it, and 3. very zealous for it, what times ſoever they are wherein we live.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Things are not therefore comely and orderly becauſe they are done of cuſtome, or commanded by authority, but are there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore both uſed and commanded (lawfully) becauſe they are comely and orderly; yet if either Cuſtome commend, or Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority command things that are ſuch indeed, wiſe, godly, and peaceable men ſhould hold themſelves (even therefore) the more bound unto them.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Church-religion, and Chamber-religion towards God he regards not, if it be not accompanied in the houſe and ſtreetes
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:40364:14"/>with loving kindneſſe and mercy, and all goodneſſe towards men.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Some weare Religion for ornament onely, that's naught, and of them that have it for uſe, ſome are led by cuſtome, ſome by admiration of ſome perſons, paſſion guides ſome, appearance others: without due examination men had beſt, 1. not leave Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion lightly, 2. Not further in any particular then we needs muſt. 3. Not at all, in the things which God hath bleſſed to our ſpirituall good.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Diſputations in Religion are ſometimes needfull, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies dangerous; becauſe (uſually) they draw the beſt ſpirits away from the heart and life, into the head and tongue: take heed of venturing nothing but words in your voyage to Heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward.</p>
            <p n="7">7. To love differences with any about Religion is a hatefull thing, wantonneſſe, affectation of ſingularity, contempt, oſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of wit, envie at ſuperiours, gratifying men with things not meet to be done; are uſuall companions of ſuch a man.</p>
            <p n="8">8. Religion hath to doe with theſe ſorts of men moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The feeble, ſuch as <hi>Nicodemus,</hi> with whom yet how our Saviour dealt is to be ſeene, <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.3.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The inconſtant, ſuch as would know every thing, but are unſteady and wavering, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.14.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The examining queſtioniſts, they muſt be awed with commands of practiſe, <hi>Luk.</hi> 18.22, 23.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The Talkeative.</p>
            <p n="5">5. The Reviling.</p>
            <p n="6">6. The Preſumptuous.</p>
            <p>It was once objected unto <hi>Eraſmus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſt mihi meus admodum ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholica, ſed ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macuri habeo plène Luthera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num.</hi> 2 Selfe-poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall.</note> eating fleſh upon a Fiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day, that that was not like a Catholike; to which he anſwered preſently, My minde is very popiſh and Catholike, but my Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke is <hi>Lutheran</hi> cleerely, I love no Fiſh; we have ſuch Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious men too many.</p>
            <p>Secondly, great care muſt be taken concerning your ſelfe Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liticall, that is to ſay, your fundamentall Lawes and conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. It is not to no purpoſe the Mulcts and puniſhments, Goales, Gallowes, and ſuch things are ordained; for hereby evill men are reſtrained, and the good live quietly among thoſe
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:40364:14"/>that aue not ſo; if the Warre make Theeves, then Peace muſt helpe to hang them, <hi>Lex à ligando diciter,</hi> the Law muſt binde men, <hi>vel legendo,</hi> becauſe men muſt read them; Read them, where? even in their execution, there they are beſt read. When God wrote Lawes, his order was to write a Ceremoniall Law for ſinnes expiation, and a judiciall Law for ſinnes puniſhment.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sen. ep.</hi> 67.</note> True it is, that <hi>Politus &amp; liberalis homo ſibi lex eſſet;</hi> a good man, every ſuch a man ſhould be a Law unto himſelfe, and I know that of <hi>Seneca</hi> well, <hi>Ineſtimabile bonum eſt ſuum eſſe,</hi> it is a royall thing to be really a man's owne; yet I ſay, let the Law be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded and reverenced, <hi>Homo dirigibilis in deum, &amp; bonum co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mune eſt ſubjectum legis canonicae,</hi> ſaith the Lawyer; now ſay I, But how ſhall this man be directed without a rule, and that rule is the Law Divine, in things of the ſoule, therefore <hi>David, Pſalme</hi> 119.126. <hi>It is time for thee Lord to lay to thine hand, for they have made void thy Law:</hi> and the Law humane in things of the body; excellent is that of <hi>Auſtin</hi> on the 76. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 10. <hi>The reſidue of wrath ſhalt thou reſtraine. Auſtin</hi> ſaith, <hi>In ipſis in probis dum, formidato ſupplicio, frenater facultas, invocato Deo ſavator voluntas;</hi> this is the excellency of the thing, that while the outward man is reſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by the feares of man, the inward man is alſo healed by prayer to God. Here then I would have marked firſt Law-giving, I would have marked with this diſtinction:</p>
            <p n="1">1. To the diſobedient for a rod the Law is given,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lex dator.</hi> 1 <hi>Duris infla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> gellum.</hi>
               </note> to which purpoſe that of 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.9. <hi>The Law is made for the lawleſſe and diſobedient, for the ungodly, and for ſinners, for unholy and prophane, &amp;c. If thou doe that which is evill be afraid, for he beareth not the ſword in vaine, for he is the Miniſter of God, a revenger, to execute wrath upon him that doth evill. Rom.</hi> 13.4.</p>
            <p n="2">2. To the proficient for a rule, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.105.
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Proficienti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus in paedago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giam.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Thy Word is a lampe unto my feet, and a light unto my path.</hi> He that in Divinity thinkes to make the Goſpell a refuge, muſt make the Law a rule; and he that in humanity thinkes to be ſafe in protection, muſt live alſo under the Lawes direction.</p>
            <p n="3">3. To the perfect for a reward, <hi>The Commandment is not grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous to us,</hi> 1 <hi>Jo.</hi> 5.3. Such men ſay with <hi>David, Oh how I love thy Law,
<note place="margin">3 <hi>Perfectiori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus in ſelatium.</hi>
                  </note> Pſal.</hi> 119.97. that is, O Lord, judge thou how I love it by this, it is my meditation day and night: <hi>Qui diligit legem, ex volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate facit, quae ſibi ſunt imperata.</hi> Infirmity is ſometimes the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:40364:15"/>Mother of Vertue, impunity alwaies the Nurſe of vices.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That it be conſidered whether there ought not to be ſome additionall Lawes, we have many for errours in practiſe, but none at all for errours in Doctrine; nay, wiſe men ſay, That it is more ſafe a great deale to be erronious, ſeditious, or ſchiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall then to reprove ſuch; and indeed there is a fearefull kinde of modeſty now amongſt men, they bluſh to helpe to beare out godlineſſe, and to ſtand for truth; but ile intreat them to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that <hi>Inutilis &amp; mortuus equiperantur in lege,</hi> an unprofitable man and a dead man the Law holds both alike, truely this world is nothing elſe; nay, give me leave to ſay, our Kingdom, our City,
<note place="margin">Non ad ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem ſed ad ſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litudinem vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vimus, inde iſta tanta coacerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, aliorum ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per alios ruen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium, Sen. De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vit. beata.</note> our very Houſes are nothing elſe but Iſlands of dreames, <hi>Non ad rationem, ſed ad ſimilitudinem vivimus,</hi> ſaith he well, Reaſon is not the rule of our lives, but example and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity of our ſelves to others, which is the cauſe of ſo many falling one upon another, and dividing one from another. When <hi>Luther</hi> began the great worke of Reformation, <hi>Albertus Crancius</hi> a Biſhop, (a man friend enough to <hi>Luther,</hi> but hope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of a ſucceſſe in that buſineſſe) ſaid theſe words unto him: <hi>Frater, Frater, abi in cellam tuam, &amp; ibi dic miſerere mei Deus:</hi> Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Brother, goe into thy Cell, and doe no more but ſigh, and ſay, Lord have mercy on me: I pray God we have not yet cauſe to ſay ſo one to another, Miniſters are divided, and Magiſtrates, and I heare wiſe men ſay, That the better part of our Magiſtrates now either are neutrall, or inclining to the worſer part; but courage,
<note place="margin">Michol. iraſiter ſed Deus dele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctater &amp;c. à Greg. ad loc.</note> Right Honourable, and you yee Senators too, I ſay to you as heretofore the Father ſaid on that place, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 6.21, 22. Here's good ſport indeed; <hi>Michol</hi> is very angry for that, for which God is well pleaſed; if any be ſo among us, let them ſo be, it's good ſport to ſee men angry for that which pleaſeth God. To conclude this point therefore, I finde an Edict of <hi>Juſtinian</hi> which goes thus,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Monicheo in loc. Rom. ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſo &amp;c. Cod. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>tit.</hi> 5.</note> If a Manichee be taken in any place of <hi>Rome</hi> let his head be chopt off; a harſh cenſure you'le ſay, but marke the reaſon, Becauſe ſaith he, whatſoever is done againſt Religion, is done to the injury of all men. I know it will be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected, I, this is that which you would have to perſecute the Saints. I give anſwer, Three Emperours together made a Law, That it ſhould not be lawfull for any of the Clergy to receive Tithes, Rents, &amp;c. Saint-<hi>Jerome</hi> writing to <hi>Nepotian,</hi> ſaith thus
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:40364:15"/>of it, It grieves not me, ſaith he, that the Emperours made ſuch a Law, but that the Prieſts by their covetouſneſſe deſerv'd it; I am loth a Law, ſuch a Law ſhould be made, but more loth good men ſhould deſerve it as they doe.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Heed muſt alſo be taken unto our ſelfe-Eccleſiaſticall, that is,
<note place="margin">3 Selfe-Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall.</note> Doctrine and Diſcipline, and thoſe two they are like the Corne and the Hedge, both needfull; ſome Doctrine is that which the Apoſtle calls for, and fore-tells that <hi>The time will come</hi> (we may ſay, The times are come) <hi>when they will not endure it, but after their owne luſts ſhall they heape to themſelves teachers, having itching eares,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.3. and for Diſcipline, our Lord hath left Keyes in ſome-bodies power, at ſome-bodies Girdle, that Scripture holds cleerely forth ſuch a thing, <hi>Matth.</hi> 18.16, 17. Now thoſe within are to be judged, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.12.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Poteſtas.</hi> 1. <hi>Concionalis.</hi> 2 <hi>Judicialis.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Et jus excommunicandi non eſt penes quemvis privatum, ſed hoc jus pertinet ad totam eccleſiam?</hi> is the rule among Divines, there is a power of Excommunicating, and it belongs to the whole Church. Againe, there is <hi>potoſtas clavium,</hi> which is, <hi>conſcionalis,</hi> belonging to Preachers onely, and <hi>judicia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis,</hi> belonging to the Presbitery; when <hi>Moſes</hi> gave the charge to the Levites to kill every man his Brother, and every man his Neighbour; <hi>And the children of Levi did according to the word of Moſes, and there fell of the people that day about three thouſand men.</hi> The Father ſaith well on that, <hi>Exod.</hi> 32, 28. <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaith he,
<note place="margin">Cauſum Dei apud populum gladiis, cauſam populi apud Deum precibus. Greg. ad loc.</note> a gallant man, &amp;c. He pleads Gods cauſe to the people-ward with the ſword, and the peoples cauſe to God-ward with his prayers. For Diſcipline in the Church of God, and its execution orderly <hi>I marke theſe foure things:</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. According to the former diſtinction, let the Miniſter by preaching ſhut the Kingdome of Heaven againſt impenitent ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and open it wide unto all them who humble themſelves; let alſo the Governours exerciſe the judiciall part.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Without the conſent of ſome Church let no man be Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicated, yea I adde, If it be a ſmall Church, and not conſiſting of many learned and skilfull men, Excommunication ought not to be done, except the neighbour Churches be asked counſell of, <hi>Zanch. in</hi> 4. <hi>praec.</hi> 756.</p>
            <p n="3">3. He that is to be caſt out <hi>Communi Presbyterorum conſenſu,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Zanc. vide in</hi> 4. <hi>praec.</hi> 756.</note> thus by a common conſent of the Presbytrie, is to be caſt out in the name of the whole Church, and by the authority of God.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:40364:16"/> 4. The manifeſt conſent of the whole Church is required, <hi>Fruſtra enim ejicitur ex Eccleſiae, &amp; conſortio fidelium privater quem populus abigere, &amp; à quo abſtinere recuſet;</hi> that is, In vaine is he caſt out of the Church, whom the Church caſteth not out, though in ſuch caſes where the conſent of the Church cannot be had: To the execution of this Diſcipline, every Paſtour and Profeſſor ought to take heed, that he have no fellowſhip with the workes of darkneſſe, but rather reprove them, yea, they ought to excommunicate them negatively, who ſhould be, but are not, excommunicate poſitively, <hi>Virga dominationis, &amp; virga diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretionis, Ruper. l.</hi> 8. in <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.</p>
            <p>I have ſome Counſells here.</p>
            <p>That the things in our way of the Church,
<note place="margin">Counſells.</note> yet in doubt and uncleered, be all of them throughly diſcuſſed; as namely, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Fathers, being viſible profeſſors, have right to the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, as well as their children (under the notion of the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of ſuch) have right to the firſt Sacrament? And why any man ſhould be ſuſpended from any one, not being before ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicated from all Ordinances? what infection is caught, and why more by men in the company of the wicked at the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, than at the Word, prayer, or the like, and other ſuch?</p>
            <p n="2">2. That our notions and diſtinctions uſed in preaching, be not made uſe of to vaile but reveale truths,
<note place="margin">Diſtinctionibus utendum eſt, non ad velandum ſed revelandum ut ubi obſourior loquendo, ibi diſtioguendo clarior &amp; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertior fuit ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritas, aliter non diſtinguiter ſed extinguiter.</note> leaſt inſtead of diſtingui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing, we come to extinguiſhing at laſt, as we have already done. The true worſhippers of Jeſus Chriſt in the ſervice of him, do willingly relinquiſh their greater part, that is, their reaſon, for ſpirituall things, are ſpiritually diſcerned, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.15. and the Spirit is to be ſerved in ſpirit, <hi>Joh.</hi> 4.24. when the Gods were en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertained in the old mans cottage, and he was bid aske what he would, <hi>Nothing at all</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>but this, That my cottage may be a Temple, and I a Prieſt to do you ſervice there.</hi> Such prayers made ſuch practiſe.</p>
            <p n="3">3. I do not thinke, nor ever yet could be brought to do, that there is any new light to be looked for, there may be a better managing of the old, prophecies indeed are now accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed, which heretofore were not, and ſo the helps are more then were, <hi>Curioſitas reos facit non peritos,</hi> Curioſity makes men ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther guilty than skilfull; that of <hi>Salomon</hi> I thinke would be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 1.9. <hi>No new thing under the Sun,</hi> and that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:40364:16"/>to men in theſe times, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 39.6. <hi>Man walketh in a vaine ſhadow,</hi> they are diſquieted, and diſquiet in vaine, the people might be more profitably taught, to walke in their old than wait for new light.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Self-deniall, ſelf-ſubmitting, much meekneſſe, a ſpirit like <hi>Davids,</hi> O let not that precious balme breake mine head, a frame of heart like thoſe that heard <hi>Peter,</hi> with readineſſe to do whatſoever is commanded, <hi>Acts</hi> 10.33. were worth all; It is our hatred of reformation, which makes us ſo unwilling to ſtoope to the yoake of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt: There is a ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing contradiction in the Scriptures, but it is but a ſeeming one, ſome preſenting to us a marvellous eaſe in the yoake of Chriſt, and a lightneſſe in his burthen; and others a marvellous diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty. It is thus reconciled, Heaven and grace are both the moſt eaſie and the moſt hard that can be, they are moſt eaſie to the ſoule which will be taught of God, and will not reſiſt his me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod by attending their owne wiſdomes. But to others they are matters of great difficulty: to God all things are poſſible, to fleſh and blood, to the wit and will of man, to the freedome of our owne choiſe, nothing is ſo impoſſible. I remember the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer of a Philoſopher to a great Prince, who had been his ſchol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, and was diſcontented at him for publiſhing his bookes, <hi>Be content, Sir,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>my bookes are publiſhed, and not publiſhed,</hi> none are ere the wiſer for them, but thoſe to whom they were read and made evident, ſo may be ſaid of this myſtery of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Care muſt be taken alſo of the ſelf-Oecanonicall,
<note place="margin">4. Self-oeca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonicall.</note> or fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily ſelfe, that is to be regarged, the houſe is, <hi>Quotidiana ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cietas,</hi> our quotidian company, our every day gueſts are th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>,
<note place="margin">Houſe what?</note> elſewhere we are but as ſtrangers, as for a time here we ſtand bound to take care of the earthly, ſpirituall houſe, yea, and an eternall one too, your ſervants are intruſted with your goods, and you are intruſted with their ſoules; Thoſe families whoſe reſolution is like <hi>Joſhuahs, I and mine houſhold will ſerve the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving God, Joſh.</hi> 24.15. their religion will be like his too. Many houſes here in <hi>London</hi> looke like the Divells Chappels.
<note place="margin">Where are your ſervants on Faſt daies and Thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving?</note> 
               <hi>Auſtine</hi> of his time ſaith thus, <hi>Is there any that yet mock at Jeſus Chriſt, I would there were</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>but one,</hi> O that there were but two, O that they could be numbred. The Phyſitian hath an axiome,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:40364:17"/>it is this,
<note place="margin">Catechizing.</note> 
               <hi>Caput malum, eſt caput omnium malorum,</hi> an evill head is the head of all evill; Maſters and fathers if they looke not to promote grace and godlineſſe in their houſes, and in the hearts of theirs, out thence is ſent furniture for the Ale-houſes, ill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſes, Goales, and Gallowes, too too too often. The Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Col.</hi> 4.15. <hi>Commend me to Nymphas, and the Church in his houſe.</hi> Here when Maſters, Parents, Servants, children, keepe houſe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in the feare of God, walking in waies of heaven, hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter alſo they come to keepe houſe together in the Houſe of many houſes eternally. See ye therefore I pray ye:</p>
            <p n="1">1. Catechizing to be regarded, a duty that we in theſe times have no thoughts of, yet <hi>Abrahams</hi> chriſtianity was hereby cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racterized, <hi>For I know him, that he will command his children and his houſhold after him, Gen.</hi> 18.19. <hi>Moſes</hi> gave it in charge, <hi>Deut.</hi> 6.6, 7. The Pſalmiſt practiſeth it, <hi>Come children, hearken to me, I will teach you the feare of the Lord, Pſal.</hi> 34.11. When our Lord ſpake unto <hi>Peter,</hi> that <hi>John</hi> 21.19. <hi>Simon, loveſt thou me?</hi> three times over, at length the command is given, and what is it, <hi>Feed my ſheep, feed my lambs,</hi> to ſignifie unto us, that lambs alſo belong to the ſheepfold of Jeſus Chriſt. You ſhall finde a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant ſent about his Maſters buſineſſe, <hi>Gen.</hi> 24. and a great buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe too, namely, to take a wife for his Maſters Sonne, and he begins his worke with prayer, <hi>ver.</hi> 12. <hi>Lord God of my Maſter Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, ſend me good ſpeed,</hi> and he ends it with prayer, <hi>ver.</hi> 27. <hi>Bleſſed be the Lord God of my Maſter Abraham.</hi> Out of what family came this ſervant, but out of <hi>Abrahams?</hi> out of a catechiſed family, ſee <hi>ver.</hi> 63. and you ſhall finde a Sonne out of the ſame family, going into the fields to meditate, obſerve it then, That Sonnes and ſervants out of catechized families, go about their buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe meditating and praying; but others out of rude and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catechized families, go about theirs, I feare, ſwearing, drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, curſing, &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Maſters and fathers of families muſt have care to get cuſtody of,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Adviros perti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net virtute vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere, &amp; exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plo regere foe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minas. Aug. l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 8.</note> to keepe cuſtody of, yea, to recover the cuſtody of, in caſe it ſhould be loſt; of, I ſay, 1. Authority. Now two pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces are in Scripture to this purpoſe, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.7. to dwell with the wife, according to knowledge, and not like a ſot, a foole, and 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.12. be an example in word, in converſation, in charity, in &amp;c. this, this is that way for men to have, keepe, and recover
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:40364:17"/>their authority, 1. maintaining their authority to direction,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Memento ſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per quod padiſi colonum de poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſione ſua, Mulier ejece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit. Hieron. ad Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pot. Ambr. ep. l.</hi> 5.33. <hi>Maximè obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate vos, &amp;c. ab uxoris con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citationibus, &amp;c. per hanc in ultimo ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plamare Job, viſne eſt diab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus. Orig. in Iob lib.</hi> 2.</note> and 2. by managing it unto good example.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Orderly knowledge, and that is knowledge of the right object, that is, Jeſus, made of the Father, wiſdome, righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, ſanctification, and redemption, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.30. 2. Knowledge in the properties, pure, peaceable, gentle, eaſie to be intreat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, full of mercy and good fruits, <hi>Jam.</hi> 3.17. 3. Knowledge in the Schoole thereof, namely, begotten in and by the publike Miniſtry, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.15. 4. Knowledge in the end thereof, namely, a pious and ſincere practiſe, ſuch knowledge I would have kept in our houſes.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Caſting quite out of the family, affectations, prating, popula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, or boaſting, out of the houſe, I ſay, and the heart too (if poſſible) of all thoſe, in whoſe religion we would have comfort. As the ſtately rivers, which (being very deepe) paſſe along ſilent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, with a ſtill and ſtately ſtreame, ſo are truly wiſe men, they are ſuch, the ſhallow brookes beating againſt ſand and ſtones, make a great noiſe indeed, but have no depth, ſo are they which trouble the whole world with their garrulity, that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruly evill, <hi>The tongue, James</hi> ſaith, <hi>is full of deadly poyſon, James</hi> 3.1.</p>
            <p>Some counſels I give here to our talking ones.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Too much good tongue is in other things vanity,
<note place="margin">Counſells.</note> in divers things prophanation, <hi>Pauls</hi> ſpeech was not with enticing words of mans wiſdome, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.3.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Some perſwade, ſome are perſwaded, but if there be not judgement going before, the former do deceive, and the latter ſuffer it, a wiſe man followes reaſon, and not paſſion, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.5.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The more low people are (commonly) the more looſe their tongues are,
<note place="margin">
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t quiſque ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jectiſſimus eſt ita ſolutiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum à linguae. Sen.</note> therefore ſee and be wiſe in quietneſſe and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence, (<hi>ſilentio &amp; ſpe</hi>) ſhall be your ſtrength, <hi>Eſay</hi> 30.15.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Heed muſt be taken to the ſelfe of ſelves, our conſciences I meane: One of the good old faſhion'd Puritans, wrote a book and called it, <hi>Chriſtian ſee to thy conſcience. Pauls</hi> Religion is, <hi>I have hope towards God, that there ſhall be a reſurrection of the dead, both of the juſt and unjuſt, And herein do I exerciſe my ſelfe, to have alwaies a conſcience void of offence toward God and toward men, Acts</hi> 24.15, 16. this, this is it that is the <hi>Index judex carnifex,</hi> of
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:40364:18"/>which the Apoſtle ſaith,
<note place="margin">Fryer and the Shoomaker.</note> 
               <hi>If our heart condemne us not, then have we boldneſſe toward God,</hi> 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.21. The Frier had cozened the cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulous Shoo-maker of a paire of Shooes, the maker dies, but the wearer lives to weare that which he never paid for; ſome years paſſe, and at laſt to the conſcience of the Fryer it comes, and he comes to make reſtitution, inquires for him, and receiving an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, That he was dead, Dead, ſaith he, hee's alive to me, I am ſure. This, O this, is the continuall feaſt, <hi>Prov.</hi> 15.15. this is the Booke,
<note place="margin">Lycurgus Plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarch.</note> 
               <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.12. <hi>I ſaw the dead, ſmall and great, ſtand before God, and the bookes were opened. Lycurgus</hi> was choſen King of the <hi>Macedonians,</hi> King, I ſay, if his brother the dead King, left not his wife with childe; the Queene is ſo, and ſends Letters pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vately to the King Elect, that if hee le gratifie her, ſhee'le take a courſe the childe ſhall never crouble him,
<note place="margin">Scientiae mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tvm parum con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcientiae.</note> for which he gives her thankes, and promiſeth recompence, but with all deſireth the childe may be borne, and then he can finde waies to deſtroy him; borne he is, and brought to <hi>Lycurgus,</hi> who kiſſeth, crown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, and proclaimeth him, chuſing rather to loſe a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome than a good conſcience. The ſcience (men tell me) in the daies we live in, is exceeding great, the good wine kept till now, the Goſpell glimpſes were never ſo lovely, the Temple is full of the ſmoake of the glory of God, old men dreame dreames, young men ſee viſions, &amp;c. All this I rejoyce in, and will rejoyce; But what meaneth then this bleating of the ſheep, in mine eares? and the lowing of the oxen which I heare? I come no where almoſt, where I finde not complaints, for want of conſcience, let me therefore ſay a word or two to this auditory, in behalfe thereof, conſcience is too ſullen to be among ſuch as cannot endure to be ſorrowfull for ſinne, conſcience is it ſelfe a booke, whereof all other bookes are but Expoſitions, our knowledge in them ſerves onely to informe us in this, or elſe we reade them to no purpoſe. Conſcience is that which tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches Lawyers beſt to plead their owne Cauſe,
<note place="margin">Praiſe of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience.</note> and Judges to judge of themſelves and for others aright; Conſcience is a thing ſo divine, and hath ſuch familiar acquaintance with God, that it will tell you (being often asked) whether God be with you, or againſt you, whether he be friend or foe: Of all newes the moſt ſoule-refreſhing, and ſin-ſuppreſſing tidings, conſcience
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:40364:18"/>is the beſt counſellor to a chriſtian, when he is alive, and the beſt comforter when a man is dead, yea, the beſt executor of his will and teſtament; conſcience is the comfort of faith, truth and uprightneſſe, and the ſhip wherein we carry that great venture of the Myſtery of godlineſſe.</p>
            <p>One word more.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Marke well that Scripture, <hi>Jer.</hi> 23.23. <hi>Am I a God at hand, ſaith the Lord, and not a God a farre off?</hi> a God, our God is every where, and conſcience is, <hi>Concludens ſcientiâ,</hi> conſcience is a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding ſcience, accuſing and excuſing are all from conſcience; if awaken, and if not, the judgement is the greater, <hi>Job</hi> 13.26. we reade, <hi>Thou writeſt bitter things againſt me, and makeſt me to poſſeſſe the iniquities of my youth,</hi> This is an heavy thing, when God comes neere a man thus, <hi>For it is fearefull not to forget that God remembers all my ſins, Hoſ.</hi> 7.2.</p>
            <p n="2">2. He that would puniſh an evill conſcience,
<note place="margin">Judas ipſe Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dae ſit accuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor. Aug. ad loc.</note> let him but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly leave it to it ſelfe, <hi>Mat.</hi> 27.3. <hi>Judas</hi> himſelfe is <hi>Judas</hi> his accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer; the working of conſcience in hell, is ſet forth by a worme that never dies, weeping, and why? for not being in Heaven, for being in Hell, becauſe they are with divells there, the worſt of all bad company; if they would cry to God and Jeſus, yet none would heare, none would pitty; and they gnaſh their teeth, againſt whom? themſelves the acters, the divells the inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, and others the provokers unto ſin; this is accuſer, judge, executioner indeed.</p>
            <p n="3">3. He that hath no conſcience, or at leaſt no uſe thereof, what ſhall be ſaid to him? when <hi>Joſeph</hi> was intiſed, his anſwer was, <hi>Gen.</hi> 39.9. <hi>How ſhall I do this great wickedneſſe, and ſinne againſt the Lord?</hi> Here is to ſee the workings of a tender conſcience; on the contrary, where there is none or a ſeared conſcience, ſee the effect, <hi>Luke</hi> 16.14. the Phariſees who were covetuous heard all theſe things, and they derided him. <hi>Timor Dei janitrix animae,</hi> Feare of God, and a ſoft heart, keepe out thouſands of ſinnes, which other men commit with greedineſſe.</p>
            <p n="4">4. He that hath a good conſcience, O what boldneſſe hath he toward God and man. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith to the <hi>Hebrewes, Heb.</hi> 13.18. <hi>Pray for us,</hi> and marke the reaſon, <hi>for we truſt we have a good conſcience in all things, willing to live honeſtly.</hi> What would our Apoſtle
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:40364:19"/>have? precious men their precious prayers, the duty God hath put upon him, and the continuall danger in execution thereof, ingage him to require theſe things, why then would he have it? I am a man that deſire, yea, deſerve prayers from you; I have a good conſcience, and who would not ſue to God in that ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication, O Lord ſave all the good conſcioned men in the world. Nay, <hi>Paul</hi> hath a good conſcience in all things, a rare preſident; many make conſcience of nothing, many of many things, but the reſt they ſlight, and ſin in not a few; few make conſcience of all things, leſſer, greater, how therefore ſhall this appeare? he is willing to live honeſtly, not compelled ſo to do, by feare, gaine, &amp;c. and willing to live ſo in all things, for ſome referre that hither, howſoever it is, you here ſee the glory of a graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous conſcience. O take heed to the ſelfe of your ſelves. <hi>Theodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> one of the Emperours of <hi>Rome</hi> was an <hi>Arrian,</hi> and one of his Courtiers deſiring to ingratiate himſelf with his Maſter, forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with became an <hi>Arrian</hi> alſo, leaving his former way of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? the Emperour hearing of it, ſtrait commands his head to be chopt off, and gives this reaſon, <hi>If,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>he will not keepe his faith to God, how will he keepe his conſcience toward man?</hi> I would all thoſe that are ſiding time-ſervers to every faction, would learne this.</p>
            <p>The ſecond Uſe which I am to make of this Doctrine,
<note place="margin">2. Uſe. Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of take heed.</note> is to give a reaſon of all theſe take heeds, for I am to ſpeake reaſon unto rationall men; nay, I am to ſpeake Religion, which is reaſon refined; Diviſion brings deſolation probably, and very often, That's enough; but there is yet more to ingage us, diviſion brings deſolation certainly, if not foreſeene, repented, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented,
<note place="margin">Chryſoſtome.</note> that's more. <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> ſaid once, <hi>If his pulpit were the higheſt mountaine, his voice like the voice of an Archangell, and his audience the whole world, he would chuſe a text for himſelfe and his time.</hi> And ſo would I for my ſelfe and our times, and it ſhould be ſuch a one as this I have choſen, <hi>Take heed of being divided amongſt your ſelves, or againſt your ſelves.</hi> Deſolation is in ſuch caſes neerer than we are aware of, there are degrees of the neer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of ruine and deſolation.
<note place="margin">Neereneſſe of mine.</note> That ground which beareth thornes and thiſtles, is rejected, and is nigh to curſing, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.8. nigh, very nigh it, <hi>Salvation is farre from the wicked,</hi> ſaith <hi>David,</hi>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:40364:19"/>and how farre? as farre as they are from it, and the waies thereof, and that's farre enough. Now If I ſhould ſay, A King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, City, or houſe divided, are neare to ruine, and in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bability like to fall one upon another, how ſhall this be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved? By a gradation from our Saviours Argument.</p>
            <p n="1">1. If any one of theſe be divided againſt it ſelfe.</p>
            <p n="2">2. But if two of theſe be ſo divided.
<note place="margin">Spirituall Geography.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. If then all of theſe be divided.</p>
            <p n="4">4. And if more than all the Church too begin to be divided, then deſolation is neare, and nearer than ſecure men are aware of. But me thinkes I ſee amongſt us ſuch Diviſions as theſe:</p>
            <p n="1">1. In Cauſes; when <hi>Gregory</hi> the ſeventh differed ſo long with the Emperours, both pretend it is for Religion, and it makes the difference a great deale the more irrecoverable.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In Principles, for the Fundamentalls are deſtroyed, and Converſion, Repentance, Charity, Duty neglected, in ſtead where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, Notion and nothingneſſe.</p>
            <p n="3">3. In Aſſumptions. Moſt Preaching is not ſound Doctrine, moſt men regard not Preaching, but ſuch, <hi>ergo</hi> moſt men muſt needs be deceived and divided.</p>
            <p n="4">4. In Judgements; we judge not aright of enemies who they are, nor aright of enmities, what they are; nor yet aright of excellencies what they are.</p>
            <p>Then comes Deſolation, this uſhers it in;
<note place="margin">What be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes firſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolate by di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions?</note> and if any aske me de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation of what? <hi>Paul</hi> anſwereth, The deſolation at <hi>Corinth,</hi> how came it, and what became deſolate? their very beſt things, Preaching became an empty thing, when one ſaid, <hi>I am of Paul, and I of Apollo, and I of Cephas,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.12. Men may cry up ſervants ſo long till they forget the Maſter, and conſider not in whoſe name they were Baptized, and who was Crucified for them, and ſo did they, verſe 13. their Communions began to be deſolate: <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith of them himſelfe, <hi>This is not to eat the Lords Supper,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.20. There is a Propheſie, <hi>Eſay</hi> 3.5. The people ſhall be oppreſſed every one by another, and every one by his neighbour; the Childe ſhall behave himſelfe proudly againſt the ancient, and the baſe againſt the Honourable; and what then, verſe 8. Jeruſalem is ruined, and Judah is fallen: this truth fits our time, the King will have a new-faſhioned Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:40364:20"/>2 <hi>King.</hi> 16.14.15. ſuch a one as he had ſeene at Damaſcus, and the Prieſt will build him one, if he will have it ſo; the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation the ancient made thereupon was <hi>Erexit Altare,</hi>
               <note place="margin">See <hi>Aug. Ad hoc.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>verſus altare;</hi> now there's Altar againſt Altar in Iſrael, Is there ſo in England too? Pulpit againſt Pulpit, Preacher againſt Preacher, it is an ill ſigne, <hi>Am<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> 6.11. <hi>God hath ſmitten the great houſe with breaches, and the leſſe houſe with clefts;</hi> nay, their hearts are divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, now ſhall they be found faulty, He ſhall breake downe their Altars, and he ſhall ſpoile their Images, for now they ſhall ſay, <hi>We have no King becauſe we feared not the Lord,</hi>
               <note place="margin">What com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany he muſt have with him which meanes to come by his owne.</note> 
               <hi>what then ſhould a King doe to us, Hoſ.</hi> 10.2, 3. We have ſpirits amongſt us, the good Lord calme them; ſuch as <hi>Melancthon</hi> ſpake of in his time, of whom if you meane to get any thing you muſt come furniſhed with a Divine and a Lawyer, yea, and a Souldier too, or elſe goe home empty. When men prove errouns it is a great wonder if they turne not turbones; unfaithfull men are for the moſt part unreaſonable men, and the unright in judgement turbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent.
<note place="margin">1 Right of Parliament. 2 King. 3 Subject.</note> There is a three-fold right which our eyes are on here in England, the right of Parliament, the right of King, and the right of Subject; we ſaid in the beginning of theſe Warres, and we ſaid truly, That the former and the latter could not be preſerved unleſſe the other, the Kings Right and Prerogative were pared a little, that it might not prove too redundant and burthenſome: Was this a good rule for Kings? and why not for Subjects?
<note place="margin">1 Right Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liamentory. 2 Independant 3 Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian.</note> Let us try a little, there is now the right Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentary, the Independant right, and the Presbyterian, they that ſit at Helme are able to Judge whether the two latter had not both need to be cut, that the former may grow the better. I onely preſſe the reaſon of all theſe Take heeds, and leave the uſe to the Lords bleſſing.</p>
            <p>The third uſe gives a direction to take heed,
<note place="margin">3 Uſe, directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to take heed.</note> our great Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet would have no man plead ignorance, and therefore hath laid downe an order, wherein we ſhall doe well to obſerve him; for, <hi>He is the God of order and not of confuſion;</hi> and we are then likeſt him when we doe things in an orderly way. They wrote a profitable Booke once, and called it as it was, <hi>Londons Survey;</hi> a great helpe to many men for many purpoſes; Here is a Survey of our Diviſions, taken by the skill of the Maſter-builder him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:40364:20"/>wherein as in a Map may be ſeene what it is that troubles our Iſrael, and yet makes us afraid. Firſt, our Kingdom Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, what are they?</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Wolfe and the Lamb lye downe together, our peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple are divided about this, they ſay, They are Wolves ſtill, and not ſo much as muſled; yet men are divided in their opinions about this, and doe not know what to ſay or think. One of the Civilians, in my hearing, once in his Speech at a Viſitation ſaid, envying againſt the conſcientious Non-conformiſts, Some of theſe Doggs muſt be tyed up, and ſome hang'd up, ſaid he, the Gentleman lives now in Towne, and hath his liberty; ſuch ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits are indeed conjured downe by Parliament Magick, but the ſinne is but pocketed, not mortified.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Our Worſhip of God now adaies is juſt like that, 2 <hi>King.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exſcind<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>inum, ſed abſcondit peccatum &amp;c.</hi> Lactan.</note> 17.28, 33. They feared the Lord, and ſerved their owne gods, the men of Babylon made one god, and the men of Cuth ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, verſe 30. We have two waies of Praying, Marrying, Preaching, Baptizing; the Miniſters drop away apace out of London: But 'tis no matter, ſay many, the Clerkes of London (moſt of them of the right ſtampe) finde out Curates enow to doe the Worke which came lately from Oxford.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Our people ſay now as heretofore they in <hi>Jud.</hi> 21.16.
<note place="margin">Pitty, how?</note> How ſhall we doe for <hi>Benjamin</hi> our brother? If a man aske them, Why would you have them pittied; they preſently give in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer that 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 28.10. <hi>Yee purpoſe to keepe under the children of Judah and Jeruſalem for Bond-men, and Bond-women unto you, but are there not with you, even with you ſinnes againſt the Lord your God?</hi> I would have the State deale with thoſe men, as God doth with poore ſinners in his dealings with them, ſo they ſhall be merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full as their heavenly Father is mercifull, and that's the rule; he reſtraines <hi>à toto,</hi> altogether, when he hinders the ſinne,
<note place="margin">True reſtreint what? 1. <hi>à toto.</hi> 2. <hi>à tanto.</hi>
               </note> all of it; ſo was <hi>Joſeph</hi> reſtrained, he reſtraines <hi>à tanto,</hi> in part, when though there be deſire, reſolution, preparation, proceſſe, and the like, yet God keepes from extremity; deſire, reſolution, &amp;c. may yet live, it may be leſſe actions deſtructive be ſtrang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led; twenty City diſcentions, and differences, what are they?
<note place="margin">Eſſentials of a well-governed City.</note> Famous Cities of old had theſe things, which they made much of, their Husbandry, Artificers, Militia, Merchandize, their
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:40364:21"/>Prieſt-hood, and their Judicature; theſe were thought Eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tialls, and indeed they were ſo, they are ſo; your Aſſociated Counties have filled your Sacks with Corne by the good hand of God, <hi>Kent</hi> was a little wilde once, but God reclaim'd them; your Artificers begin now a little to hold up their heads, your Militia hath been the Gallantry and envie of England, this ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry day remembers me of <hi>Nubury</hi> Battell, but your Miniſtery de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cayes, it decayes exceedingly, <hi>London</hi> had never more need of, nor leſſe care for a good Miniſtery. Some men ſay, It is ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious to pay Tithes; our people ſay, better a great deale to turne their Tithes into Gifts and Oblations, and then they are offered at another Shrine. Let no man, I beſeech you, curſe your Judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catories, for want of juſtice doing to all.</p>
            <p n="1">1.
<note place="margin">Counſells.</note> Let God ſpeake one word to you, and marke it well; <hi>For the tranſgreſſion of Jacob is all this, and for the ſinnes of the houſe of Iſrael, Micah</hi> 1.5. All this, all which? ſee verſe 4. the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines are molten, and the Vallies cleft; What is the tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion of <hi>Jacob,</hi> is it not Samaria? And what are the high places of Judah, are they not Jeruſalem? A ſtrange kinde of ſpeaking, Samaria and Jeruſalem are the great places, the great ſinnes; London and Weſtminſter are ſo, the Idolatry of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, the evill example of England, the poiſon of places. O amend your waies, your Manna-loathing, your giddy-headed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, yea Londoners, for feare you make God and good men weary of you.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Let me ſpeake another word to you, 'tis but a word or two, <hi>Magiſtratui cives, Magiſtratus legibus,</hi> till the people obey their Governours, and till they obey the Lawes, no good will be done.
<note place="margin">Boni domo, malus civis.</note> Every good man is not preſently a good Citizen; you ſay, Keepe thy Shop, and it will keepe thee; I ſay, Keepe your Lawes, and they'le keepe you. The two great Ordinances of Magiſtracy and Miniſtery have been the envie of wicked men in all Ages of the world. <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſaies, There were three great ſinnes, Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, <hi>Exod.</hi> 32. puniſhed with the Sword, the burning of the Roll, <hi>Jerem.</hi> 36.23. puniſhed with Captivity, but Diviſion, <hi>Numb.</hi> 16. in <hi>Corah, Dathan, and Abiram,</hi> puniſhed with the Earths dividing and ſwallowing them up.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Our Houſe-Diſſention, what? O what not? Father againſt
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:40364:21"/>the Sonne, Sonne againſt the Father; Husband againſt Wife,
<note place="margin">Houſe Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſions.</note> Wife againſt Husband; and indeed a mans enemies are thoſe of his owne Houſhold. The Canoniſts have one rule, <hi>Omne malum à ſacerdotibus,</hi> no evill that comes not from the Prieſts: and <hi>Luther</hi> hath another very blunt, but very true, <hi>Nunquam periclitater religio infiniter reverendiſſimus,</hi> Religion never comes into grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter danger than among the right Reverend;
<note place="margin">Preaching ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed, deviſed.</note> whether the Prieſt be moſt, or the people moſt in fault he cannot tell; one thing I know, that what the Apoſtle ſaith is true, <hi>There are that creepe into houſes, and lead Captive ſilly women laden with divers luſts, ever learning, and never learned.</hi> I thinke things will never goe well till we of the Miniſtry be by Ordinance as from God, ſo from man injoyned to preach all our errours, without partiality Truth-ward, all our Hereſies whatſoever Hell-ward, all our own ſheepe (if we have any) to Repentance, Obedience, &amp; Duty-ward; and all other mens ſheepe either ſtolne, or ſtragled to their owne Fold-ward againe, ſo ſhall we pray for ours, as the Chriſtians heretofore for their government.</p>
            <p>The fourth Uſe will informe us,
<note place="margin">Uſe 4. Chriſt miſtaken.</note> That here is to be ſeene Jeſus Chriſt in a miſtake indeed, where is he not ſo to be ſeene; I meet him ſo almoſt in every place, in not a few Pulpits great mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtakes, and fundamentall, never more Hay, Stubble and Straw built upon the foundation than now; this muſt be amended alſo. He ſaid to the purpoſe, That <hi>Optima Reſpublica quae maxime legis, minimè rhetores audit,</hi> If it be the beſt Common-wealth that obeyes rather than diſputes, I think it will be found alſo the beſt Church that doth ſo. It will be a good warning to let the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple know that there may be much miſtaking about truth; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore obſerve:</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Lord Jeſus cannot be divided, a truth to which the Apoſtle ſets to his teſtimony, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.12. why then if they ſhall ſay unto me, <hi>Behold, he is in the Deſart, I'le not goe forth, behold, he is in the ſecret Chambers, I will not beleeve it, Matth.</hi> 24.26. I will even reſolve to ſeeke him where I have found him, and that is even walking in ſuch publike Ordinances as theſe in the midſt of the ſeven golden Candleſticks, <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.13. No greater deceit can be obtruded upon a man, then to ſet him to ſeeke there for a thing where we know it is not, or where
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:40364:22"/>(indeed he is not) though we did not know the ſame.
<note place="margin">Jugling about Antichriſt juſt aſ about Chriſt.</note> How is the <hi>Jew</hi> deceived in his Meſſia? How the <hi>Turk</hi> in his <hi>Mahomet?</hi> but even ſo. The type of Antichriſt is in <hi>Daniel,</hi> himſelfe in <hi>John,</hi> now the Papiſts ſeeke for himſelfe in <hi>Daniel</hi> where his type is, and in <hi>John</hi> where himſelfe is; they are afraid to ſeeke him for feare to finde him.
<note place="margin">Counſells.</note> I would not have us to deale ſo in ſeeking for Jeſus Chriſt; in the publike ordinances, <hi>He hath bin found of thoſe that ſought him to their comfort, and to their converſion.</hi> To ſend a people to looke him where he is not, for feare they ſhould finde him were a ſad ſinne to be guilty of; I did never thinke, nor yet doe, that he is rather to be found in the private than in the publike meetings; nor that he is at all to be found in many of thoſe places which the people are made to beleeve are better than Church-meetings.</p>
            <p n="2">2.
<note place="margin">The Divell and Sin caſt out both one way.</note> There are not two waies of caſting out Beelzebub; What, doth Satan caſt out Satan? Doth the Independant caſt him out one way, and the Presbyterian another way? Indeed all our work in the Miniſtery is nothing but to caſt out Divells, for every ſin is a divell, and every Miniſter is or ought to be a man indeavou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the ſtrength of Jeſus Chriſt to caſt out theſe Divels out of himſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> others, &amp; all the people of God; It is a work that hath been done heretofore, and the diſpoſſeſſed have given thankes therefore to God. So then, as our Lord asketh one queſtion, ſo I'le aske another; he asketh, <hi>By whom did your children caſt him out?</hi>
               <note place="margin">As our fathers ſerved Chriſt, ſo muſt we in this particular.</note> and I aske, By whom did our Fathers caſt him out? <hi>Paul</hi> excellently, <hi>F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> though you have ten thouſand inſtructers in Chriſt, yet have you not ſo many fathers, for in Chriſt Jeſus I have begotten you through the Goſpell.</hi> Are they now then become your enemies be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they did you good? Take heed you doe not caſt off your Preachers, their old precepts, and your old practiſings, till at length you grow from ſomething to nothing; thoſe whom God hath honoured with the converſion of many, are ſcarce honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red now with the company of any; of any, I ſay, no body al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt to heare them. None of thoſe who muſt acknowledge, even them to be the inſtruments of Gods mercy to them.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The worke; the very buſineſſe of Jeſus Chriſt, is the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying of the workes of the Divell, ſo ſaith the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 8.8. Heare yee then and be not proud, for ſurely God hath
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:40364:22"/>ſpoken this thing, our Miniſtery and our Government, while they are acting ſo to deſtroy the workes of the Divell, they act with Chriſt, and they act for Chriſt, and Chriſt will doubtleſſe (whatſoever fooliſh men ſay) act with them, and act for them. Let us therefore give up our ſelves to this ſervice, let us make this our buſineſſe, God hath made it ſo, and reſolve to ſay with <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard, Nitius me privares amaro mors, vitae meae uſu quam fructu,</hi> it were better to loſe life it ſelfe than the purpoſe to which God inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded it. There are two great Workes of the Divell to be acted againſt in our ſinnes.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Decreaſe of duty muſt be acted againſt,
<note place="margin">Our publike concerning Duties, our Faſts faile, Ale-houſes and Tavernes about <hi>London</hi> take more money on thoſe daies then they doe till ſuch daies come againe almoſt, ſome of them have bragged ſo. <hi>Cui bonites ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve De<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, ui Deus ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Chriſto. Tert.</hi> Sins mereſe.</note> certainely if duty faile as it hath done, and doth daily, we ſhall all faile with it. I heare ſome ſay, I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>le ſing no Pſalmes at home, or at Church ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, unleſſe I be ſure they be all Saints I ſing with; I heare others ſay: I'le not Catechiſe my children, for feare I ſhould make Hypocrites of them. Whence came this Doctrine forth? Are theſe indeed the words of truth and ſoberneſſe? Heretofore good Chriſtians have found benefit by the old way of duty, and yet not truſted to it, or any thing but the onely to be truſted; For what goodneſſe is there without a God? and what God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hout a Chriſt? Heretofore theſe things were thought to be the way to the Kingdome, though not the cauſe of reigning. Betweene truſting to a worke done, and not doing it when it ought to be done, is a great difference.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Increaſe of ſinne muſt be acted againſt, increaſe of all ſin, but eſpecially of ſuch kinde of ſinne and wickedneſſe as becomes a man's ſinnes, that they are alſo Gods puniſhments; becauſe they beleeved not the Goſpell, becauſe they received not the love thereof, God gave them up to beleeve a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ye, 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.11. <hi>If any man ſhall doe his will, he ſhall know of the Doctrine whether it be of God or no, Jo.</hi> 7.17. Theſe two ſins increaſe mightily amongſt us, the want of love and truth, and the want of practice thereof; under which two notions indeed the whole of the ſinne of our time is committed. Between wit, learning, authority,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience there hath been a great queſtion which ſhould be the greateſt, but it was alwaies granted to experience to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> for it being converſant about ſenſible things, and by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> tained, doubtleſſe it doth not ſo eaſily erre in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>bject, as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:40364:23"/>courſes and deductions of skill. We have had gracious experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences of the converſing with, and finding of God in publike or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, and of the ſweetneſſe that is to be found in the love of practiſe, and of duty; if any man have found another, a newer, a nearer way to communion with God; I doe not grudge him his, nor will I (till I ſee more) be drawne out of mine owne. Prudence among the Ancients had wont to be painted thus;
<note place="margin">Prudence what?</note> An Hand full of eyes, with five fingers, long, ſtrong, and very white and faire; that is to ſay, Memory, underſtanding, circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpection, fore-ſight and execution; if there be prudence amongſt us, as I hope there is yet much left, nor doe the prudent keepe ſilence in the gate; I hope we ſhall remember our peace, how yet young it is, underſtand the things that make for it, looke about and ſee who cauſeth diviſions; fore-ſee that which our Lord ſaith will be the iſſue, and doe execution impartially on the Peace-diſturbers.</p>
            <p>The fifth Uſe leades us to ſee,
<note place="margin">5. Uſe, Dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</note> That there is a rule of Condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Diviſions, not all of them, nor promiſcuouſly are they to be adjudged againſt, but regularly and with diſcretion. Some have ſaid,
<note place="margin">Cauſe of all errour.</note> and thought, That the cauſes of all the errours of our times have been ſuch as theſe, miſ-application, fallacy, cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulity, ſupine careleſneſſe, and the cleaving unto antiquity, and authority over-much, without ſuch diſquiſitions as become thoſe that would <hi>Try all things, and hold faſt that which is good.</hi> And if I ſhould ſtay a little here, and take theſe into conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſurely much, and exceeding much might be ſaid. Men are made up of miſ-applications, they are preached and practiſed, if fallacy and ſophiſme ever would paſſe for current reaſoning and Religion, ſurely they are now gilded over to deceive the eyes of the ſimple; credulity, ſuch as the wiſe man hints, <hi>The foole beleeveth every thing</hi> is the Idoll of the times, and when all theſe goe before, you muſt needs thinke what followes after amongſt many men, even a reſolved negligence of every thing till every thing be eſtabliſhed;
<note place="margin">The King of <hi>Navarre</hi> to <hi>Beza.</hi>
               </note> or if they ſeeme to doe or ſay ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, it is but as the King of <hi>Navarre</hi> ſaid to <hi>Beza,</hi> That he would goe no further to Sea than he might ſleepe aſhore, when pleaſed him; or as the Polititian ſaid, He would follow Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion as he followed a Horſe, not too neare for feare he ſhould
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:40364:23"/>kick, and hurt him: A man's fooliſhneſſe brings him into for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mality, and that into nothing. But this is that which undoes our times and people, they have falſe ſelves, and they have falſe Glaſſes whereinto they looke themſelves,
<note place="margin">Falſe ſelves too truely looked unto.</note> and a falſe Glaſſe will not eaſily ſhew a true face; marke then theſe falſe-ſelves-follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. Men will ſay, They have a care of all theſe ſelves, and they have a ſelfe of Religion. Then for anſwer:</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Selfe of Religion men ſpeake of ſo much,
<note place="margin">1 Times Selfe myſtically.</note> it is a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion without Reformation; I read men as well as bookes, and heare men ſcoffe at the great Reformation, at our great Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers too; but theſe are great ſenſualiſts, a Generation of men and women, concerning whom our Apoſtle is very plaine, <hi>They ſpeake evill of the things they know not,</hi> 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.12, That place of the Author to the <hi>Hebrewes</hi> is to be marked diligently, its de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne, and the Doctrine therein, as exceeding fit for our times;
<note place="margin">Reformation.</note> the firſt Tabernacle ſtood onely in meats and drinkes, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers waſhings, and carnall ordinances impoſed on them, untill the time of (Reformation) which word I heare finde onely in the New Teſtament, and may be expounded thus;
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> till the ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of better judging; ſo then I conclude that till the time, ſuch a time onely, a time of Reformation ſome things were to conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue; who therefore deſtroyes Reformation, deſtroyes one of Gods deſignes: ſpeake not againſt Reformation.
<note place="margin">Common Prayer.</note> And here now for our Booke of Common Prayer, men are divided ſtrangely. For:</p>
            <p n="1">1. Some aske, Shall we have none of this, and complaine that for want of formes of Baptizing &amp;c. for the Country, their Miniſters make but halfe Marriage, and commit ſuch whole abſurdities in the Baptizing of Infants, Adminiſtration of the Lords Supper, &amp;c. That it grieves ſome, cauſeth others to jeere<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and ſhames the Ordinance, and that Solemnity wherewith the things of God ſhould be performed. The <hi>Slavonians</hi> ſeeking to Pope <hi>Formoſus,</hi> that they might have Service in their owne Mother Tongue,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Slavonians</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt.</note> it was debated in a Counſell, wherein a voyce was heard from Heaven, ſaying, <hi>Let every Spirit praiſe the Lord, and all Tongues confeſſe him:</hi> Whereupon for that time it was granted. This is found in <hi>En. Silveſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:40364:24"/> 2. Some ſtubbornely, againe ſay peremptorily, Wee'le have none but this; in this we have been brought up; thus our fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſerved God;
<note place="margin">Raboldus.</note> and as they, ſo we. The Duke of <hi>Frizland, Raboldus</hi> by name, about the yeare of our Lord 900. being per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded, as he pretended, to imbrace Chriſtianity, as he went to be baptized, and had the one of his feet in the water, he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded of the Biſhops, <hi>Whether all his fore-fathers were damned?</hi> the Biſhops anſwered, more raſhly then wiſely, That <hi>they were all damned,</hi> whereupon the Duke pulled back his feet againe, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Then will I alſo be damned with them.</hi> This was a reſolution ſcarce becomming a man, much leſſe a wiſe or noble man. This diviſion of ours, which every foot gives out a crack of diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, which makes a loud noiſe among our people, I take not upon me to determine any thing in, Who am I, that I ſhould guide our guiders? onely this I ſay, That were it but conſidered, in how many places every Lords day, ſomething is done this way in not a few pariſhes, and that not without railing againſt the Parliament, and the perſwading the people that they live under tyranny and perſecution, becauſe this is withdrawne; how much better were it, either to let us every day be drawing neerer unto covenanted Uniformity?
<note place="margin">Covenanted uniformity.</note> or elſe to give ſatisfaction, that what is done this way, is done by a granted connivency? I muſt needs confeſſe, I finde this a very heavy burden to many, and ſome ſeeing this, and ſome other preſſures, are ready to ſay, We ſhall ſee the day that the Parliaments friends will be the greateſt ſufferers, even they whoſe zeale cauſed them to do and ſpeak moſt in worſt times.</p>
            <p n="2">2.
<note place="margin">2. Selfe-Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty.</note> The ſelfe of Liberty which men ſpeake of, what is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, I judge at, but what is pretended, that I heare, and it is a Goſpell liberty, ſuch as wherewith Chriſt hath manifeſted us, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.1. even the Sonne of God hath made us free, ſuch a free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and under ſuch a purchaſe at that (on a right and well grounded perſwaſion of it) a man would willingly rather looſe himſelfe, and what is his, than the leaſt part of his right and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt in it: Let us therefore give eare againe to our <hi>vox populi.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1.
<note place="margin">In all things.</note> Liberty in all things! theres a Religion indeed, ſay ſome, and they are ſcandalized, they ſit them downe, and ſay, Is this it I have fought for, ſaith the Souldier? is this it I have prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:40364:24"/>for, ſaith the Divine? Sure I was greatly miſtaken, I wrote preached, and prayed for, not libertiniſme, we had too much of that before, but ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ictneſſe in Doctrine, Diſcipline; every way the reines were too looſe afore, and to throw them now quite into mens necks, what will become of this? Gods people are chid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den for ſparing any of the Heathen, <hi>Jud.</hi> 2.3. Muſt we tolerate all and mingle with them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Liberty in nothing! Here's a government indeed,
<note place="margin">In nothing.</note> tyranny and peſecution this is, and no leſſe, and here I heare men rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling at and envying againſt the Parliament and Aſſembly, and who not? as though they were abridged of ſome of that their liberty which was borne with them, or beſtowed on them; I heare men exhorted to prepare for ſufferings; and one Doctrine I met withall the other day, preſſed ſtrongly, and I thought ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied as ſtrongly, the Doctrine was this, <hi>That it was Gods new Teſtament deſigne, that his new Teſtament Saints ſhould patiently ſuffer under old Teſtament counſells and perſecutions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Our liberty, which is temporall, is ſet downe, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10 29.
<note place="margin">Liberty. Temporall.</note> why is my liberty judged of another mans conſcience? there in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed we have a liberty, and ſuch a one as is beſt when offence is neither given nor juſtly taken thereby.</p>
            <p>Our liberty ſpirituall is held fotth in 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.16. as free,
<note place="margin">Spirituall.</note> and not uſing your liberty for a cloake of maliciouſneſſe, but as the ſervants of God, we are rather as free indeed, than altogether ſo, and yet whom the Sonne of God makes free, they muſt be free indeed, in a rightly underſtood freedome.</p>
            <p>Our liberty celeſtiall is expreſſed, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.21.
<note place="margin">Celeſtiall.</note> the creature it ſelfe alſo ſhall be delivered from the bondage of cor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uption, into the glorious liberty of the children of God. Now here is liberty truly compleat, and indeed ſuch it is, as is a liberty from ſinne and cauſes thereof, ſuch a liberty in the full, as is there promiſed in part, where God ſaies, <hi>He will put his people in a place of their owne, and the wicked ſhall trouble them no more,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 7.10.</p>
            <p>I thinke there is no more but Liberty-carnall,
<note place="margin">Carnall.</note> of which a man ſhall need to reade nothing but what he ſees ſome men take liberty to ſweare, to drinke, to ſerve God when they will, and how they will, to refraine publike meetings, &amp;c. For which he
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:40364:25"/>that will plead, I ſay of him, as heretofore <hi>Joaſh</hi> ſaid unto all that ſtood againſt him, <hi>He that will plead for him, let him be put to death while it is yet morning, Jud.</hi> 6.31. Mine advice there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in this point is, Foraſmuch as this is a very weighty point, and much, inſiſted on, a point about which ſo much diviſion is, and not a little of it (it may be) ſuch as wherein men fight with ſhadowes rather than adverſaries.</p>
            <p>That the liberty be:</p>
            <p n="1">1.
<note place="margin">Deliberated.</note> Soundly deliberated, by whom? how? why? when? in any caſes, to any perſons to be granted, queſtions fit to be left unto ſome exactly learned Caſuiſt in matter of Divinity, and to ſome ſubtill Stateſman in matter of policy; for by whom? if the Parliament, then power is in them? how ſhould it be given?</p>
            <p n="2">2.
<note place="margin">Delivered.</note> Sweetly and meekly delivered, without bitterneſſe, no mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſity, it is unprofitable, it doth no good at all, much harme ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and if delivered, to whom and on what termes, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der what notion.</p>
            <p n="3">3.
<note place="margin">3. Selfe.</note> The ſelfe of Doctrine which men ſpeake of, for they would have teaching too is a Doctrine yet without Diſcipline: pleaſing things, a Goſpell utterly without the Law, no cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiſement, all of love, nothing of feare, conſtraint is very un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>Goſpell like, men thinke and ſay ſo too, <hi>Meliores amor flectit, ſed plures timor,</hi> Love bends many, but feare bowes more, was the old rule. Againſt the light of Doctrine no man will be ſo bold as to barke; To aske whether light be pleaſant, is a blinde mans queſtion;
<note place="margin">Why moſt men care for no Diſcipline.</note> to aske whether knowledge be ſweet, is an ignorant mans queſtion; but to aske whether divine light is moſt ſweet, is a prophane mans queſtion, but no Diſcipline. The rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of this, no wiſe men ſay to be becauſe the Nobility is to blame to ſay no more, and the Gentry filthy, the Clergy flatter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and the Communalty ſo exceedingly overwhelmed with prophaneneſſe, that they would willingly go downe into the pit, and not be troubled; as if it were an eaſe to go to hell ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily, or as if the ſpirit of Satan were got into the ſons of men, that they ſaid to all the meanes of ſaving them, as the Divels ſaid to our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>Why art thou come to torment us bofore the time?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="41" facs="tcp:40364:25"/>
            <p> They were brave dayes our people thinke, when</p>
            <p n="1">1. The greater ſort in their Adulteries. Whoredomes, &amp;c. were all above, quite above the reach of any diſcipline; the Courtiers durſt ſay to the Preachers as hee to the Prophet, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy no more at <hi>Bethell,</hi> for it is the Kings Chappell, and the Kings Court. <hi>Amos</hi> 7.13. Impiety increaſing with migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty increaſes, and no reaſon, but becauſe his old friend Impunity clapt him on the back with incouragement, ſuch as we read, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 12.4. who is Lord over us? let the Almighty depart from us, who is the Lord? &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The other ſort, none of them were under the laſh, if able to turne white ſheets into white ſhillings, they were comutacioners, changes very ſad, we chang'd our glory in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our ſhame, when <hi>Parva lequor quidvis, Nummis preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus, apta, eveniet, clanſam poſſidet arca Jovem:</hi> How unlike to thoſe times was this where the charge runs thus, If the Delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent would have pardon, let him aske it with his owne teares,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Si veniam reus ſperet, petat cum lacrimis, petat totius eccleſiae fletibus, Amb. de pen. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 16.</note> yea, and with the teares of the whole Church, it was ſo in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient times.</p>
            <p n="1">1. To the willing to learne I propoſe Saint <hi>Auſtin's</hi> rule, I think it is a good one, and it is this, He that goeth againſt reaſon is no wiſe man: and he that goeth againſt the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture is no ſober man; and he that goes againſt the Church is no peaceable man: There are but two places appointed for the cleanſing of a ſinner: earth and hell, there alſo, but two meanes, fire and water: He that waſheth not himſelf in the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of penitentiall teares here, muſt lye hereafter in flames of fire to indure, paines unutterable, and without end.</p>
            <p n="2">2. To the willing to ſubmit, I ſay one word more</p>
            <p>Of great experience doubtleſſe, of Gods dealings, and ſoule refreſhings was that weeping prophet, who in the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches name delivered that, <hi>Lam.</hi> 3.27. it is good for a man that hee beare the yoke in his youth: And indeed I never read but of two yokes, and they are one of Doctrine, and the other of Diſcipline: and it is good, God ſaith,
<note place="margin">The yoke of God.</note> to beare them both.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, The Family ſelfe which I ſee men making ſo
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:40364:26"/>much of,
<note place="margin">4 Selfe econo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>micall.</note> it is riches, and the pompe of the world, riches gotten with wrong and held to the hurt of the owners thereof. Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven is amongſt moſt people a kinde of ſuperfluity and hang-by; gaine is their Godlineſſe; the Religion of <hi>Epheſits,</hi> God wot, and no other, then whom God hath bleſſed from the dunghill; O how uncharitable, proud, cruell, diſdainfull, for earth pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viding, and heaven neglecting they are; over-reaching our bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren in bargaining is now counted a vertue, indeed a matter of oſtentation,
<note place="margin">Quod Gillias poſſidebat, omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um quaſi commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne patrimonium erat. Fitipſius precordia liberalitatis ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buit, et domus e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ius quaſi quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam muni ficen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae officina.</note> but why is it? even becauſe the word of God muſt needs be true. Fooles make a mocke at ſinne, <hi>Prov.</hi> 14.9. The ſaying of old was of <hi>Gillias,</hi> that what he had was every Mans patrimony; the cleane contrary is very true of very many men, what every man hath is theirs if they can lay their hands thereupon: O the noble ſpirits of <hi>Luther</hi> and ſuch manner of <hi>Hem: Germana illa beſtia non curat aurum,</hi> when it was ſaid of him, bribe him, tempt him with money: no, (ſaith my authour) hee's a man regards no coine, that ſpeech of his, when ſuch great, offers were made unto him is very heavenly. He re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſeth with theſe words <hi>valde proteſtatus ſum, me nolli ſic ſatiari ab eo.</hi> I have ſtrongly engaged my ſelfe, not to be ſatisfied with meane things from God; noble minded <hi>Baſil</hi> gave the Emperour <hi>Valentius</hi> this peremptory, but gallant anſwer. <hi>Haec pueris non Chriſtianis offer.</hi> Sir, you ſhould offer theſe to children, and not to Chriſtians, <hi>Bernard, ſicut mea non ſibi place<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t, &amp;c.</hi> As what I give thee, cannot be pleaſing to thee without my ſelfe, ſo Lord, the contemplation of what thou haſt given us doth refreſh us, but not enough, without thy ſelfe: and the reaſon that he gives is very precious,
<note place="margin">True ſpirituall pride.</note> 
               <hi>Habet enim vera ſapientia ſui generis ſuperbians,</hi> for true wiſedome hath its kinde of ſpiritually wiſe pride, and will not be long, or alwayes contented with any thing, leſſe then the living God; Somewhere it is ſaid in Scripture, <hi>I have ſmitten mine hands at thy diſhoneſt gaine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Some <hi>Apollos</hi> mighty in the Scriptures, whoſe Preaching is like thunder,
<note place="margin">Precept for rich men.</note> and his life like lightening; I would have ſet upon it to tell, yea, and charge thoſe rich men too.</p>
            <p n="1">1. With that precept, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.17. Charge them that are rich in this world, that they be not high minded, nor truſt
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:40364:26"/>in uncertaine riches, but in the living God: the more rich and plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull God makes men, the more humble harmeleſſe, and heaven providing to be, laying up for themſelves a good foundation, good works they are not loſt, but laid up, and for foundations to eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity. <hi>Dorcas</hi> her coates, God hath them in remembrance; the great Preacher, who gave the lewd rich man a viſit, ſpeakes thus to him, after ſome time; Sir, God be mercifull to you if he will, and pardon your ſinnes, which I beleeve not; and bring you to Heaven, which is (as your caſe is) impoſſible.</p>
            <p n="2">2. with that example too;
<note place="margin">Example for them.</note>
            </p>
            <p>With that <hi>Luke</hi> 12. where Chriſt befooles the men that are on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly worldly wiſe, and no more <hi>ex roſis, non ex ſtellis, plures epicuri quum aſtronomi,</hi> the wiſe man ſaid, and what a fearefull thing will it be after a man hath ſeene all other gaine, to ſit downe and ſigh, becauſe of the ſoules loſſe. <hi>Dives</hi> and <hi>Lazarus</hi> their compariſon in regard of outward and preſent things, is without compariſon; but if you looke upon them after death, you ſee they are as farre aſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der as Heaven and Hell. <hi>Didiceram elatus domine, iniquitates meus, diſcam humiliatus juſtificationes tuas,</hi> If men be lifted up, they minde nothing but their ſinnes; but if they be caſt downe, then they remember Gods mercies: and indeed, how much better is it to be broken with afflictions unto ſalvation, then to be preſerved by proſperity unto evils, which God will not pardon, 2 <hi>Reg.</hi> 24.4.
<note place="margin">Selfe of ſelfe in the world what?</note>
            </p>
            <p>Fiftly, The ſelf of our ſelves, what is that? the thing that men deſire herein is either no Conſcience, or none uſe thereof, men think them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, leaſt themſelves when indeed they are moſt ſo; and on the contrary, when they can out-brave ſin, out-live tenderneſſe of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, and ſay as he ſaid of old to his reprover. Thou foole,
<note place="margin">Stulte tu nonne putas me vereri Deos cum talia faciam? Nero to Se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>:</note> doſt thou beleeve that I beleeve there is any God, when I doe theſe things? then they are themſelves they thinke; I have heard men give thankes to God, for that which indeed is one of the heavieſt judgements under Heaven: namely, they thanke God they were never troubled in all their lives, <hi>ubi non hoc bellum, ibi pax diabolica,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Auſtin.</hi> Where there is not this warre, there's a deviliſh peace. How happy was <hi>Paul</hi> in his ſmiting to the ground, his blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, diſtreſſe of Conſcience, prayer and the like? you know the ſtory, <hi>Act</hi> 9. the excellency of godly ſorrow, and the effects therof,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:40364:27"/>2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.11. are ſet forth unto us, if we would hearken to Gods holy word, as in the body ſo in the ſoule; there is but the wound and the medicine in the body, and but the ſinne and the ſorrow in the ſoule, no more to be regarded.</p>
            <p n="1">1.
<note place="margin">Chryſoſtome's reſolution con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning ſwea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</note> Some zealous man for God, muſt doe as heretofore, <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtome</hi> did when he was to preach to the <hi>Athenians,</hi> it ſeems they were a people much given to ſwearing, and he proteſts that untill they leave their ſwearing he will never leave preaching againſt it; even ſo would I have the Miniſters of God to reſolve never to leave preaching againſt falſe bottomes, till our people be ſetled up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a true one: and our falfe bottomes are not a few whereon men ſettle themſelves. <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.23. and then will I profeſſe unto them, I never knew you.
<note place="margin">Falſe bottomes</note> 
               <hi>Depart from mee all yee that worke iniquity,</hi> profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion without practiſe; the miſtaking of the meanes of grace and holineſſe, for grace and holineſſe it ſelfe. Selfe-love, and thinking our ſelves to be ſomething, when we are nothing; formality and meere out-ſideneſſe in Religion, <hi>opus operatum,</hi> and the ſerving of God with an action done: theſe are the things which breed ſo many miſcariages amongſt us.</p>
            <p n="2">2.
<note place="margin">Fundamentals.</note> But how ſhall this worke be done? No other way, but by preaching and preſſing the fundamentals; Such texts as that <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.3. except yee be converted yee cannot enter into the Kingdome of Heaven. <hi>Verily, verily, I ſay unto thee, except thou be regenerate and borne againe, thou canſt not enter into the Kingdome of Heaven, Iohn</hi> 3. Such texts I ſay as theſe are, they muſt be preach'd, opened and applied. The Fathers tell us in good earneſt, that they did never beleeve another man had need to be converted, untill they were converted themſelves; this is downe-right dealing, I like it very well, and it remembers me of what <hi>Lactantius</hi> ſaith. Were there (ſaith he) but 7 wiſe men in Greece?
<note place="margin">If but 7 wiſe men in Greece, none at all.</note> no, but 7 onely, why then there was none: there muſt be ſome more wiſe men to judge of their wiſedome, otherwiſe, a wiſe man is not a wiſe man in the judgement of a foole. Wiſe men thinke that Religion is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly decaying in <hi>England,</hi> becauſe a yong Hipocrite makes an old Atheiſt ſure; and there are now ſo many of the firſt, that in the next Century we thinke there will be not a few of the laſt; our God provide for his people.</p>
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:40364:27"/>
            <p> The great Prophet alwayes preached a way,
<note place="margin">He that preaches not a way, prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches nothing.</note> and ſo muſt the leſſer doe; it is dangerous to preſuppoſe a people to be Saints, and holy, and ſo to preach unto them; it were better to teach them how to be ſo, and to try whether they be ſo or no. Better I ſay, I thinke, to aske our Saviours queſtion, <hi>whom doe you ſay that I am?</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Queſtions.</note> 
               <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.15. then to aske that queſtion <hi>Acts</hi> 19.2. <hi>Have you recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the Holy Ghoſt ſince you beleeved,</hi> let the godly wiſe conſider it, and they that have the worke of the harveſt in their hands. Not a few I beleeve in this great City, puffed up with their perſwaſion of themſelves and others of them; if they ſhould come to cleare dealing withall, muſt ſay that they had need to be inſtructed in the doctrine of Faith, Baptiſme and the Holy Ghoſt too. Well the Scripture ſpeakes of a good conſcience, <hi>Acts</hi> 23.1. of a cleare conſcience, <hi>Acts</hi> 29.16. of a pure conſcience 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.9. of a purged conſcience, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.14. of an evill conſcience <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.22. of a weake conſcience, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.12. and of a ſeared conſcience, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.2. which of theſe now is thy conſcience, it behoveth thee to take notice of.</p>
            <p>And take this with thee, whoſoever thou art.
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Ad ſui preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem.</hi> 2 <hi>Ad preſervatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem univerſi.</hi>
               </note> I never heard a deſcription of vertue that pleaſed me better then that <hi>Brevis et ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra definitio virtutis est, ordo amoris, Aug.</hi> vertue is nothing elſe, and grace too, but the very ordering of our love; take heed of a heart and conſcience loving diviſions which God hateth.</p>
            <p>The Philoſophers ſay there is a twofold motion, in naturall things; one whereby they move unto the preſervation of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; and another, whereby they move unto the preſervation of the whole univerſe. Water naturally moves downe-ward; never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe, for the generall good, it will move upwards rather then faile; ſo ſhould Religion and good conſcience doe; move to our private good, ſo, as that withall we remember that we ſerve our generation, and be uſefull alſo. It is an ill ſpirit, and a worſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, that hath ſo much minde of its owne things, that it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gards not the things of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Uſe. </seg>6</label> The 6. uſe teacheth us Gods courſe of convincing men.
<note place="margin">Courſe of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincing men.</note> How to convince I ſay, a work of the Holy Ghoſt; a work, which is ſometimes, as immediately going before converſion, as the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning before the day, as in thoſe <hi>Act.</hi> 2.37. they were pricked in
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:40364:28"/>their hearts, and they ſaid, men and brethren what ſhall we doe to be ſaved? and in all the ſuch like inſtances whereſoever. For, of this let men be well aſſured, that whenſoever God doth clearly reveale himſelf to the ſoule:
<note place="margin">Marks of a man rightly convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced.</note> He preſently worketh this great work of conviction, and in this order.</p>
            <p n="1">1. God maketh a man to beleeve his miſery by ſin, and to be much troubled for it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. He conſulteth in this caſe what to doe, and is much troubled about it.</p>
            <p n="3">3. He is exceedingly broken in heart, and humbled to the duſt.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Above all things in the world he deſireth forgiveneſſe of thoſe ſins which with a free heart he now confeſſeth.</p>
            <p n="5">5. He forſaketh all for the aſſurance of that pardon, and highly prizeth it; yea, all things droſſe and dung in compariſon of it.</p>
            <p n="6">6. He applyeth Chriſt and his promiſe, lives therein, groaning after all excellencies, effects, and evidences of pardon. In this or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der holy Scripture ſets forth conviction to be wrought; But yet further it may be marked, that</p>
            <p n="1">1.
<note place="margin">Gods worke ſometimes.</note> Conviction is indeed the work of the great God, and of him alone, he is the heart-opener: Whoſe heart the Lord opened, that ſhe attended unto the things which were ſpoken of <hi>Paul, Act.</hi> 16.14. For it is not the willer, nor the runner, but God that ſheweth mercy, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.15, 16. of old the Lord had theſe wayes to convince his people.</p>
            <p n="1">1. There were Philoſophers, Prophets, or Poets, and Orators and Wiſemen, of whom what vice was it which was not brought into diſgrace? what vertue was unperſwaded? that a man may ſafely ſay of ſome of them, that they left unto poſterity more clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and Prints of Divinity, than all the books of the Schoolemen put together. So (as I remember) ſaid <hi>Bucer</hi> alſo of <hi>Seneca.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bucer's</hi> ſaying of <hi>Seneca.</hi>
               </note> They had their proverbs, and voyces of men, publickly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, as that againſt the <hi>Cretians</hi> was a proverb, <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.12. The <hi>Cretians</hi> are alwayes liars, ſlow-bellies, and evill beaſts; and this in my Text a proverbiall ſentence alſo.</p>
            <p n="3">3. They had the works of God, by which he intended to leave men without excuſe, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.20. As raine and fruitefull ſeaſons, <hi>Act.</hi> 14.17. Nay, they had yet more, the naturall knowledge where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:40364:28"/>they knew the Law, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.32. and the naturall conſcience whereby they did by nature the things contained in the Law, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.14. All this I obſerve to let you ſee how zealous God is to keep afoot this work, to teach us that it ought not to be loſt, our Lord in his time uſed it, and convincing preaching will be found to be the lively Ordinance, when all is done.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Sometimes he will have men to doe this work,
<note place="margin">Mans worke when God will have him do it.</note> and then hee conveyes into them his power, and bears a preſence with them; thus he was with the Apoſtles, <hi>Peter</hi> in a great converſion and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction; <hi>Paul,</hi> and others alſo; <hi>Apollos</hi> was a man inſtructed in the way of the Lord, and he mightily convinced the Jews, and that publickly, ſhewing by the Scriptures, that Jeſus was the Chriſt, <hi>Act.</hi> 18.25, 28. Such ingredients as theſe goe to the making up of this ſpirituall medicine, as to convince by anſwering, to ſilence by anſwering, <hi>Job</hi> 32.12. to convince by reproving, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.16. to convince by preaching, <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.9. to convince by chiding, rebuke them ſharpely <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.13. to convince by correcting with all autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.15. to convince every way, to convince any way that is lawfull, and by the word warranted. I read of <hi>Cicero,</hi> that pleading for <hi>Ligurius,</hi> Mine Authour ſayes the bills fell out of <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar's</hi> hand, the bills of his accuſation, as it were forced by the elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence of the pleader; a great power there is in conviction.
<note place="margin">Naturall and Spiritual thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Wee learn from all this that hath been ſaid, that men are excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding hard to be brought to any thing of God, they muſt be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced, the naturall thunder is the voice of God, ſo is the ſpirituall too, that is exceeding ſubtle, ſo is this, it divideth between the marrow and the bones, the naturall thunder breaks a peeces, what reſiſts it onely, ſo doth the other, it is like fire, and the hammer that breaketh the ſtony rock aſunder.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Some men there are, whom of all others,
<note place="margin">Who ought ſooneſt to be unvailed.</note> I would have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction to finde out; namely, the ſubtill, cunning, crafty ones, ſuch to be ſilenced, is a great victory, a very great conqueſt. When the Word of God, the truth of Chriſt comes off like <hi>Stephen, Act.</hi> 6.9, 10. The Libertines, and Syrenians, and Alexandrians and thoſe of <hi>Cilicia,</hi> and <hi>Aſia,</hi> were diſputing with <hi>Stephen,</hi> but they were not able to reſiſt the Spirit, and the wiſdome by which he ſpake, O then the word of God and thoſe which handle it, come off like
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:40364:29"/>
               <hi>David</hi> from <hi>Goliah,</hi> with the head of the champion in his hand. The Herodians Court-flatterers, a ſycophanticall generation, ſee how convincingly our Saviour deales with them, <hi>Matth.</hi> 22.21, 22. <hi>Render to Caeſar the things which are Caeſars, and unto God, the things which are Gods, and they marvelled.</hi> We have a like inſtance <hi>Joh.</hi> 8.7. He that is without ſin among you, let him caſt the firſt ſtone at her, and they that heard it, being convicted, went out one by one. The Goſpel is alwayes the power of God unto great things, but never more viſibly, ſo then when we can ſay with the Apoſtle, Where is the wiſe? where is the Scribe? where is the diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> this world? Hath not God made fooliſh the wiſdome of this world, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.20. As <hi>David</hi> prayed, ſo I would we ſhould doe in a time of diſtreſſe, that the <hi>Ahitophels</hi> of our time may be infatuated.</p>
            <p n="4">4.
<note place="margin">Meanes for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction.</note> How may a man beſt convince enemies, ſuch as our Lord here had?</p>
            <p>I anſwer, even as our Lord did, ſurely that will be found to be the very beſt way. His direction is the onely infallible one, therein we may abide, therefore obſerve,</p>
            <p n="1">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 1. Our Lord ſhews his courage in both Preaching and practiſe, notwithſtanding in the preſence of his profeſſed adverſaries; He taketh all opportunities to do good, by his Doctrine and Miracles, and hereby convinceth them, it ſhameth them amongſt us, who at ſuch a time can bend their tongues like bows, for lies, but are not valiant for the truth, <hi>Jer.</hi> 9.3.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 2. Our Lord ſpeaketh home, &amp; to the conſciences of his adverſaries, makes them witneſſe of the truth he ſpeaks againſt them, ſo did <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muel,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.5. and ſo did <hi>Joſhuah</hi> alſo, <hi>Joſh.</hi> 34.22. ſo ought we to doe, and it ſerves to chide them, who jangle about words to no purpoſe, the leaſt truth laid home to the conſcience would doe more good.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 3. Our Lord vindicates and defends the truth againſt oppugners, the truth of the Reſurrection, againſt the Sadduces, and convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth them, <hi>Matth.</hi> 22. of tribute paying to <hi>Caeſar,</hi> againſt the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rodians, and convinceth them; He that bids us be ready to render a reaſon, ſhews himſelf ready on all occaſions ſo to doe; It reproves them that are Nicodemites and Neuters in theſe ſad times, of which ſort we have not a few.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:40364:29"/> 4. Our Lord retorts upon his enemies, their owne arguments, fights with them, with their own weapons, he caſts out devils as their children doe, this is that convinceth, if the Maſter-builders of <hi>Iſrael</hi> would obſerve, it may be there were arguments enough to be found in our adverſaries to overthrow both them and their cauſe, ſo ſome have done Popery.</p>
            <p n="5">5.
<note place="margin">When con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced and no more.</note> And one word more I have to ſay to all ye that are the blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheming Cavileers of this generation, of you I know there is not a few, If once yee be convinced, and no more, behold the glaſſe of theſe men, in which I intreat you look your faces, the glaſſe I ſay which Ieſus Chriſt hath opened you to look in.</p>
            <p n="1">1 You will fall into extremity of ſin.
<note place="margin">More ſin.</note>
            </p>
            <p>If you bee convinced and no more, if you have the flaſhes falling upon your eyes, and no more, if you taſte of the powers of the life to come, and no more, if you weepe for ſinne once, and laugh, and to it againe, you will fall into extreames of ſinfull courſes, your later end will be worſe then your beginning, you'le beginne in the Spirit and end in the fleſh wofull and everlaſtingly, ſo will bee the conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſuch a man doubtleſſe.</p>
            <p n="2">2. You will fall into extremity of judgement,
<note place="margin">More judgement</note> into extremity of judgement I ſay, when God makes ſinne our puniſhment for our ſinne, and one of our evils to be the reward of another, it was theſe peoples caſe, ſee ver. 30.31. they fall into a ſcattering where Chriſt ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thereth, and from thence the next ſteppe is into the ſinne againſt the holy Ghoſt, a blaſphemy not to be forgiven.</p>
            <div type="application">
               <head>Some Councells.</head>
               <p n="1">1. See thou take heede of exalting thy wicked ſelfe, ſo did the Scribes and Phariſees, and above them Ieſus Chriſt muſt not bee, though God the Father give never ſo cleare evidence of him: Yee that ſet your ſelves in your wayes above the way God hath owned, heed this;</p>
               <p n="2">2. Love not cavilling ſcornes, nor jeering ſcoffs, they are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>becomming, Ieſus Chriſt is but a fellow with theſe fellows, verſ. 24. I do not know what ſinne a proud ſpirit is not fit to fall into.</p>
               <p n="7">
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>7</label> 7. The ſeventh and laſt uſe,
<note place="margin">Danger.</note> gives us in a word or two of the danger in caſe all this be not diſgeſted, touched by our Lord in all thoſe expreſſions, ſhall be deſolate, ſhall not ſtand, an houſe will fall upon an houſe, and the like; theſe doubtleſſe are all added to this purpoſe that we might be more cautelous, for if ruine, deſolation
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:40364:30"/>and ſuch things will not ingage us to take heed of diviſions, nothing at all will.</p>
               <p n="1">1.
<note place="margin">1. deſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> Deſolation will come; will come ſhall I ſay? Nay rather let me ſay, and I ſhall ſay true; Deſolation is come, it is at hand already, <hi>But when he ſaw the multitude,</hi> (ſaith St. <hi>Matthew) hee was moved with compaſſion on them, becauſe they fainted, and were ſcattered a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, as ſheep having no ſhepherd: Then ſaith hee unto his Diſciples, The harveſt truly is plentious, but the labourers are few, Pray yee therefore the Lord of the harveſt,
<note place="margin">who to by pittied.</note> that he will ſend forth labourers into his harvest, Matth</hi> 9.9.36 37. 38. The field of God is untilled and deſolate, the gardens indeed of the Congregationall, the Church way, theſe are dreſſed, trimmed and fine, theſe are weeded, rowled, digged, dunged, what not, not any thing amiſſe; But the poore people in the Field, on theſe no pitty of God, no pitty of Man falls; <hi>Ninevehs</hi> 6000000. makes me remember them which knew not the right hand from the left: I am confident there are not in any place in the kingdome of <hi>England</hi> ſo rude, heatheniſh and ignorant a peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple as are to be found in the ſuburbs of <hi>London,</hi> and the adjacent pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces thereabouts, no greater people nor living more inconſiderable: Now he that looks here may ſee deſolation; I would have theſe fields tilled, and ſome of that feed which here falls in the high way and in the ſtony places, caſt there abroad, who knowes but that it may there (ſome of it) fructify by the bleſſing of God, and bring forth fruit in abundance.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Inſtability will be in Religion,
<note place="margin">2. Inſt bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity.</note> nay I pray to God that inſtabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity be not for Religion; ſome ſuch tenets I heare and ſee already: Some men glory in having ſo dark and doubtfull a behaviour, that no man can tell what to make of them; the more ſcepticall a man is now, the more religious hee's thought to be, to walk as a ſtaggerer, neuter, and unreſolved one, as if a mans Religion were ſtill to chooſe: is this becomming them whom God bids to be perſwaded in their own minde? <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.5. Nay, ſuch men as theſe do affect to have, and indeed bear the bell away for the wiſeſt men in the Countrey, becauſe they will utter themſelves no further than if need bee they may keep their retreat fair, and have the wind on their backs.</p>
               <p>If ſuch a one as I might ſpeak without offence, I would here inſert two words of warning, the firſt to my ſelf and ſuch inferiour ones as I am; wherein I would deſire to obſerve</p>
               <p n="1">1 Vnder what Banner Gods holy warre beſt proſpereth, <hi>Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:40364:30"/>I mean, namely, neither under ſtrength, nor might, nor wiſdom,
<note place="margin">Ru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>es for preaching</note> but his own ſpirit, <hi>Zach.</hi> 5.7. let us take heed therfore of pleaſing our ſelves too much in our own inventions.</p>
               <p n="2">2 They that draw their people on to the carnall admiring of their parts and perſons, teach them a leſſon which <hi>lames</hi> cries out againſt, <hi>the having of the faith of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt with respect of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons,</hi> I am.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Let not be forſaken the maine truths of God, and the chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nell of wholeſom doctrin to run into ſome od muddy creek of our invention for feare wee looſe our peace, with ſeeking to get the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples praiſe.</p>
               <p n="4">4. I would wee might all be as little carnall in preaching Ieſus Chriſt as may bee, and as much ſpirituall as poſſible might bee; the evidence and demonſtration of the ſpirit that is it.</p>
               <p n="5">5. I would our ſubjects might be often changed, and if we ſee wee have preached Mercy up, till Duty bee quite done, then change the ſubject, and preſſe originall ſinne; preach Selfe-denyall, Mortifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, the New creature, taking up the Croſſe, Preparation for death, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>The ſecond unto the people of this City.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The end of preaching is Common edifying, nothing elſe,
<note place="margin">And for Hearing.</note> Know it, and lay it for a ground; every thing is beſt uſed when to the end which God appointed it.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Take heed of partiallity and the balking of any mans miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry that is faithfull; God is able to fit a truth to thee, which yet was not ſtudied for thee.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Do not catch at new points, forſaking old grounds, it is the common fault of <hi>London</hi> hearers, they have better braines then either hearts or lives.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Eye the Miniſter, in not thy relation to him, nor in thy know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of him, nor according to the infirmities that are in him, but as the diſpencer of the myſtery of Chriſt, that will beſt prepare thy ſpirit God being intreated) that thou mayeſt be like one of <hi>Peters</hi> hearers, willing to hear whatſoever is commanded.</p>
               <p n="3">3. An houſe will fall upon an houſe, that is the third danger, and it is a danger if our Lord hath ſo ſet it downe to bee: Houſes are but of four ſorts, as the Private houſe, the Politique houſe, the Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſticall houſe, and the houſe of Clay the Corporall houſe, and all theſe are in continuall danger of falling one upon another, if diviſions ceaſe not, For we read,</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:40364:31"/> 1. <note place="margin">4. Houſes.</note> A difference that fell among the Private houſes and Families, concerning the ſpies, <hi>Numb.</hi> 13.31.32. Some ſaid one thing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the land, ſome another.</p>
               <p n="2">2. A difference that aroſe betwixt them concerning the Altar, <hi>Joſh.</hi> 22. There ſome ſaid one thing, ſome another; but the cauſe of feare being good, a good God gave a good effect unto it.</p>
               <p n="3">3. A difference about the Sacrament grew, the poore were diſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by the rich, and one ſeparated from another, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. but were at length reconciled by a good God, whoſe inſtrument was a carefull Miniſtery, then ſetled among them, preaching againſt (what they then practiſed) Self-diviſions.</p>
               <p>Now what diſcouragements were then uſed againſt diviſions,
<note place="margin">Our prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching.</note> the ſame will be now uſed to quell the laſt of theſe, and we hope in God with the like ſucceſſe, for I begin with the laſt firſt, preaching a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it.</p>
               <p>As for the ſecond difference,
<note place="margin">Our bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>threns diſcovery.</note> It was eaſily blowne over with a faire diſcovery, which mended all when their mindes were once knowne, a courſe which we hope will bee taken in Gods time by our good brethren, that jealouſies may all bee blowne away, and unity ſhine forth.</p>
               <p>But the third is of moſt importance,
<note place="margin">The peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</note> that relates to the Reformers and the Reformation too, and is of evil conſequence, ſome ſay they give too much to the Parliament, ſome ſay wee give too little, and too many amongſt us are like the uncomfortable ſpies, which ſay, this difference will not end without more blood ſhed.</p>
               <p>I ſhall impart my minde freely, and it is this.</p>
               <p n="1">1. I dare not but beleeve, that the God which brought the Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament out of the greater will alſo (if our ſinnes hinder not) bring them out of the leſſer difference,
<note place="margin">Faith.</note> that wee may once ſay with <hi>Paul,</hi> He hath delivered us, and will deliver us with ſtrength of beleeving comfort.</p>
               <p n="2">2.
<note place="margin">Modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</note> Though it hath been obſerved that never any people have been earneſt for a tolleration, but thoſe which have had great, and it may be too great power with, and influence upon the preſent Governours, yet my councell is, that our moderation appeare, for feare leſt wee ſpoile ſome of their prudentialls (not yet come to maturity, and of which ordinary men are not able to give an accompt) with our want of diſcretion, prudence, piety, prayer, things wherein if wee bee obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diently and waitingly converſant, we act where wee ſhould doe, and move orderly in our own ſpheres.</p>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:40364:31"/>
               <p> For the houſe Politique in <hi>Iſrael,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Houſe po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litick.</note> there indeed we read of diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons alſo, and thoſe were either at the time of the ſetling of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, or after it was ſetled, or laſt of all at ſuch time when God for ſin of King and people, quite took away the Law-giver from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>Iudahs</hi> feet, that he might make away for the birth of the King of kings, according to the prophecies of truth, which went before of the Lord the <hi>Meſſiah.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Nothing I ſee is herein neceſſary for our marking and ſome profit,
<note place="margin">Cauſe.</note> but 1. the cauſe of all theſe ſtirres and civill diſſenſions which I find to be, 1. The ſinne of the people, whom how eaſily it is to bee per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded they are not well governed, woefull experience tells us, thus they rejected <hi>Samuel</hi> and God in him, God himſelfe tells them ſo. 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 8.7.</p>
               <p>The ſin of the Governours too, For if men lifted up to ſuch a top of preferment, 2. Then are indeed as <hi>Nazianzen</hi> phraſes it <hi>inſtar Funambulorum,</hi> like dancers upon ropes, all whoſe ſafety is in their uprightneſſe, and they hapned to go awry, ſo that with their ſin the people, and with the peoples ſin the King comes to be ſmitten, then ſword and peſtilence ſhewed themſelves forth to be Gods ſervants, for to execute his ſore diſpleaſure on thoſe that had offended, as is to ſee throughout the Hiſtory of the Kings and Chronicles of <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly for the cure,
<note place="margin">Cure.</note> we ſhall apparently find that the ſins of the Governours of <hi>Iſrael</hi> they were. 1. Pride;
<note place="margin">Pride.</note> 
                  <hi>Davids</hi> ſin in numbring the people, 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 24. <hi>David</hi> will ſee how many hundred thouſand he may call himſelf the king of; and the Lord lets him ſee that he can ſoon eaſe him of ſome of his ſubjects, and cures this diſtemper by letting a great many thouſands fall of; the peſtilence untill the the ſame King <hi>David</hi> come &amp; beg that God will ſpare ſome of them, whom his ſin hath ſpoyled.
<note place="margin">Intruſion.</note>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Intruſion and uſurpation: <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zziah's</hi> ſin, hee'le intrude into an office, and deſtroy an ordinance in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> a ſin which God pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed with an earthquake, as the Prophets ſay that ſpeak in his ſinne and with diviſions, <hi>then God ſmote the great houſe with breaches and the little houſe with clefts</hi> Amos. 6.11.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Blood, the ſinne of, <hi>Manaſſes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">blood.</note> he filled <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent blood, and the catalogue of his offences ſtands recorded for poſterity to looke upon and dread, 2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 33.</p>
               <p>Such an affliction God ſent this King, ſo ſanctified as that he
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:40364:32"/>waſhed away the eternall guilt of blood from his ſoule; but that God may let men ſee what a ſinn blood is, there ſtands a peece of Scripture ſtill as if written with a pen of Iron, or the point of a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amond; it is in the 2. <hi>Kings</hi> 24.4. <hi>He filled Jeruſalem with innocent blood which the Lord would not pardo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>;</hi> that is to ſay, as to the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall guilt.</p>
               <p>If in theſe glaſſes then we ſee any glimpſe of the face of our houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>politick, help with your prayers I pray you, you that ſee the danger, that it may be prevented.</p>
               <p n="3">3.
<note place="margin">Church-houſe.</note> The New Teſtament beſt holds forth unto us the diviſions of the church; houſe, when the Goſpell came to be preached, and the Church to be eſtabliſhed with Governours &amp; government, then the envious man ſowed tares, and in both doctrine and practiſe men ſhewed themſelves of what ſeed and ſide they were, the woman or the ſerpent. Some held no reſurrection at all, ſo the <hi>Sadduces,</hi> ſome held it was paſt already; ſome erred one way and ſome another, and men full of faith and the holy Ghoſt, had their miſcarriages, and went not with a right foot unto the Goſpel; I am of <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith one and I of <hi>Apollos</hi> ſaith another, and a third ſubſcribes himſelf for <hi>Cephas.</hi> Thus was the houſe of the church divided, and one fell upon another, ſome preached Chriſt of envy; ſome one way, ſome another. All this while I obſerve two Rules to guide men, one di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine which <hi>Paul</hi> gives and takes, well ſaith he every way Chriſt is preached, and therin I doe and will rejoyce; if any glory acrew to Jeſus any way, I hope I ſhall be glad of that, and the Lord will gett himſelf glory ſometimes when, and where, we doe not think of.</p>
               <p>The other rule I walke by is humane, and it is this. <hi>Quiſquis vel quod poteſt, arguendo corrigit, vel quod corrigere non poteſt, ſalvo pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis vinculo excludit, vel quod ſalvo pacis vinculo excludere non poteſt equitate improbat, firmitate ſupportat, hic eſt pacificus &amp; ab iſto male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicto immunis.</hi> Eſa. 5.20 Aug. That is to ſay, he that by reproving corrects that which he can, or that which he cannot correct, doth (peaceably) exclude, or that which he cannot peaceably exclude, diſalowes, or wiſely beares with; he is a peaceable man and free from that curſe, <hi>woe unto them that call evill good, and good evill, that put darkneſſe for light, and light for darkneſſe, that put bitter for ſweet, and ſweet for bitter.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Houſe cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Laſtly the houſes of clay, the houſes corporall, they'le be falling
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:40364:32"/>one upon another, if they be devided againſt themſelves and among themſelves, and ſome Spirits make no more of claſhing even a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the greateſt of authority, than he did of fighting, which ſaid, <hi>let the young men ariſe and play before us,</hi> 2. <hi>Sem.</hi> 2.14. onely here is the difference; that in the battell there, there was a name, <hi>Helkath-Hazzuzim,</hi> the field of ſtrong men, verſ 16. But all theſe claſhings, conceits, invectives, alarms, araignments &amp;c. they get no name a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong wiſe men, but weake, worthleſſe, and empty nothingneſſe; For it is a judgement for the childe to behave himſelfe proudly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the ancient, and the baſe againſt the Honourable, <hi>Eſai,</hi> 3.5. <hi>Roma forte egrotat ſed ſanitas a talibus?</hi> I would intreat theſe men to learne.</p>
               <p n="1">1 Obedience, Not blinde, that wants diſcretion; nor implicit obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, that wants truth; nor ſlaviſh and ſeditious obedience, that wants juſtice; But that they be content to let Theologicalls have an influence upon their ſoules, Politicalls upon their bodies, and Pruden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tialls have ſome guidance of thoſe unruly evils, their tongues, ſo of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten ſet on fire of Hell.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Moderation; that they bring not a railing accuſation: Its ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding unbecoming men that would be thought godly, to vomit and belch out ſuch blaſphemies againſt things I am perſwaded many of them know not; for all ſuch books, I ſay of them as heretofore it was ſaid of the Popes Cannons; <hi>Canones multi facti fuere in favo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem Canonum — Concilia per Canones ij vero per ſemetipſos — Ignorantes admirantur, Doctirident, Supereſt una litura,</hi> that is, Many Canons were made in favour of the Canons, the Councels were guided by the Canons, and they by themſelves; ignorant peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple they admire all this, but the learned ſmile: Nothing is wanting but one good daſh to blott them all out, or a good fire to burne them all.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The laſt danger is, wee ſhall have caſting out of them which indeed had more need to hold together; there is a twofold caſting out of a man; the one more private, whereby every Chriſtian is bound to forbear the familiar converſing with ſuch as are openly wicked and ſcandalous in doctrine or life.</p>
               <p>The other is a more publick caſting out of an incurable perſon, who will receive no good, but is likely to doe much harme in the Church by infection, if hee bee ſuffered; let him therefore bee an out-caſt.</p>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:40364:33"/>
               <p> And whereas there are two degrees of excommunication, the former ſeparating from all brotherly ſociety, with the members of the Church, and the latter cutting off from the body of Chriſt, which is nothing elſe, but that fearfull <hi>Anathema</hi> and curſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced by the Church againſt him who is diſcerned to have ſinned the ſinne againſt the Holy Ghoſt; the former of theſe two is called a caſting out, a rejecting, <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.10. a caſting or thruſting out of the Synagogue, <hi>Iohn.</hi> 9.22. the Churches cenſure, and that which He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks and others are ſubject unto.</p>
               <p>If it be asked, who muſt do this? I anſwer, The whole Church; but eſpecially the Paſtors, leſt their remiſneſſe or familiarity with ſuch, make the people more bold with them; for it is meet that the whole Church ſhould have knowledge, approbation, and conſent in that which concerneth the whole.</p>
               <p>If it be further asked, how farre they muſt be avoyded, and caſt off? I anſwer, Holy Scripture muſt bee conſulted with, and there we finde</p>
               <p n="1">1. Generally it is ſet down, <hi>Matth.</hi> 18.17. where it is comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded that ſuch as will not heare the admonition of the Church, ſhall be accounted as Publicans, and as Heathen men that is, as ſuch with whom we will have nothing to do, for <hi>Iohn</hi> 4.9. <hi>the Iewes meddle not with the Samaritans.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. More eſpecially, 2 Theſ. 3.6. <hi>withdraw your ſelves from every one — with ſuch a one no not to eat.</hi> 1. Cor. 5.11. <hi>receive him not into your houſe, neither bid him God speed.</hi> 2. Epiſt. Iohn. 10.</p>
               <p>And yet all this muſt be underſtood wiſely and with theſe cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
               <p n="1">1. This cenſure infringeth not any of the bonds of civil right and ſociety, an excommunicate Magiſtrate remaineth a Magiſtrate ſtill, and ought of all Chriſtians ſo to be acknowledged and obeyed, the enſure onely makes them as no Chriſtians, not as no Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtates.</p>
               <p n="2">2. This cenſure looſeth not the bond of common humanity, but that every thing muſt bee adminiſtered to ſuch a one as is neceſſary for the preſerving of his life, <hi>Romanes</hi> 12.20. <hi>If thine enemy hunger, feede him, If hee thirſt give him drink.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:40364:33"/> 3. The cenſure takes not away naturall right, nor houſe, nor bed, nor table, muſt be denied to excommunicate husband or wife; the cenſure doth not make them to be no husband, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, maſter, wife.</p>
               <p>The cenſure doth not looſe all the bands of ſpirituall ſocie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, but that notwithſtanding it wee may and muſt love the excommunicate in the Lord: ſecondly, pray for him, though not with him: thirdly, admoniſh and rebuke him ſtill: fourth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, upon his repentance, receive him like a brother, as before. The cenſure then</p>
               <p n="1">1 Taketh a man off from communion with Gods people in word, Sacraments, and prayer; and indeed renders him as a dog or ſwine, for whom theſe holy things are unmeet, <hi>Math.</hi> 6.7.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Taketh a man off from converſe, ſo farre as neceſſarily we are not bound to them; as is to be ſeen in the behaviour of <hi>Iohn</hi> the Evangeliſt towards the Heretique <hi>Corinthus,</hi> when he found him in the Bath,; and of <hi>Policarp</hi> towards <hi>Marcion:</hi> out of <hi>Irenaeus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And if any man ſhall ſtumble at that, why the cenſure ſhould not extend to the ſhutting of men out from all Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances whatſoever, and ask why now they ſhould be admitted to the word: I anſwer, it is the indulgence of the Church only, for in the Primitive times it was not <hi>Ambroſe</hi> kept <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>odoſius</hi> the Emperour being excommunicate quite out of the Church of <hi>Millaine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Some caſt themſelves out of the Church as <hi>Demas,</hi> forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king <hi>Paul,</hi> and imbracing the preſent world, ſome were caſt out and reſtored againe, and made better by diſcipline, onely we never read amongſt them ſuch unkindly caſting out of one anothers hearts, as wee have amongſt us; And as to the other, ſomething I would ſay alſo.</p>
               <p>Firſt, I thinke wee have beene ſomewhat too nimble in caſting out, and ſeeking power ſo to doe, before wee well knew who wee had in, and amongſt us, I heare
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:40364:34"/>many men ſay that the very aſſaying of the Presbyterian Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment too too ridgidly hath not made a few Independents, neuters, raylers, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Secondly, I thinke wee have beene ſomewhat too flow in the ſecuring our kernell of doctrine from hereſies, and gratings upon the foundation, before wee were too zealous of the ſhell of Diſcipline; Wee had done well I beleeve, had wee given our adverſaries leave to have beene blemiſhed with all the innovations, exorbitan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies in writing, ſeparations, precipices, petitions, petu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancies, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>While in the mean time we had acted nothing, but as God the two Houſes and the preſent opportunities had gone before us: I conclude with ſome councells fit for our times, ſuch as theſe.</p>
               <p>Firſt, Men doe not diſpute now adayes, but brawle and wrangle; In the handling of controverſies, no mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration nor meekeneſſe is uſed: Wee ſhould conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that the things wee know are the leaſt part of thoſe wee know not: If more reverence were given to the word of God, the holy Spirit implored, prayer made to God more frequently, If care were had to abſtaine from all curious queſtions, and practicall and profitable things, preached and preſſed, wee ſhould I am perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded agree ſooner, and God would I am of opinion bleſſe us better.</p>
               <p>Secondly, In Controverſies of great moment doe but ſee the Devils cunning, Hee ſtirres up men to hatreds, pride, reproachfull ſpeeches: Alas, the authour of er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour muſt bee handled friendly, and if chidden at any time, it muſt bee done without bitterneſſe; arguments uſed, fitted not to the perſon, but the thing; And if wee could alwaies aime at this, that not our opinion, but Gods truth might bee glorious, And that whenſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever wee enter into preaching, or writing, or confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, or the like, Pride might be put off, and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty with humility and moderation out on, there
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:40364:34"/>were ſome hope wee might live to ſee the day, that wee might live like brethren, and the Lord might delight to dwell amongſt us.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, Heede ought to bee taken that by the two great Authorities no injury bee done; I meane firſt, That by the authority of the Church, neither Man nor Doctrine bee raſhly condemned, that difference bee wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly made between the points of Faith, which are neceſſary to bee beleeved, and certaine, and things controverſall; that opinions bee weighed with much of judgement, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection too, wherein the beſt Scale will bee the word of God; that men be very tender of things neceſſary to be known and beleeved, that the things flowing from principles be obſerved, and in the reſt there be kept a Brotherly concord.</p>
               <p>Secondly, That the authority of the Magiſtrate be alſo very venerable, the Hangman not called in to be a Moderator or Umpire in controverſie of Religion; the Magiſtrate not made an inſtrument to execute every foole and knaves luſt and mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; nor in caſes of errour, and humane lapſe, recantations injoyned for feare of puniſhments.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, Many times doctrine is depraved and ſpoyled, Men not obſerving it, and this cometh to paſſe either from the doctrine it ſelf, becauſe indeed the fineſt bodies ſooneſt putrifie, or becauſe changes by little and little, are made inſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, as the turning of the houre wheel: Sometimes miſcariages come and are not ſeen becauſe of a great fame of learning and holynes in the teacher, and ſometimes becauſe of the ignorance and negligence of the hearer. Surely the way to preſerve purity of doctrine, is carefully to cleave unto the very words and phra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of holy ſcripture, quietly to give leave unto the modeſt and moderate uſe of any mans gifts, publick peace preſerved; Dilli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently to cry down all luſt of contention; and ſoberly to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of, and ſubmitt the authority and irrefragibility of coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſells, if ſuch be in them.</p>
               <p>Fiftly, Becauſe diſſembled ſanctity is double iniquity, therefore it would bee obſerved that ſome men maintayn
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:40364:35"/>their own name no better any way than by detracting from all mens elſe, and then they indeed act their own cauſe when they ſeem to ſtirre in the cauſe of God: Very angry they are if any man contradict them; too too ready to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches and flyings out; then they come to truſt their own wit, parts, and labour, more than God; and if there bee not the more mercy, fall to ſinning againſt knowledge, and conſcience: Without all controverſie to the preſerving of holineſſe and goood manners, Cenſures Eccleſiaſticall are very needfull; which yet have been and may be ſo exerciſed as that it may bee truly ſayd of them, the Devill rebukes ſinne; many wiſe men think and that upon good grounds too, that publique Pennances are neither needfull nor uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full.</p>
               <p>Sixtly, I think that a modeſt liberty of opinions concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Religion, is much againſt Satans kingdome, becauſe I know that he deſires to take away all deſire of enquiring af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Truth; the people think they may caſt off all care and ſtudy of Religion to their Miniſters; and are like him who when hee was asked by his Miniſter, How many Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments there were? gave that anſwer to him, Sir you can tell.</p>
               <p>Two things I think wee ought to bee very carefull of; Firſt, to ſet down exactly the marks of true and falſe Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, which may ſtand as ſo many Dooles or Landmarks, as well to ſhew men where they ought as where they ought not to go.</p>
               <p>Secondly, to conſider well how they which govern Church and Common Wealth, are uſually incited againſt Truths profeſſors, I confeſſe I have thought, and yet doe, exacted confeſſions from our people very inconvenient; for if Miniſters carry themſelves lovingly, they will winne their people to more profitable diſcoveries a great deale another way.</p>
               <p>Seventhly, How Satan labours that neither truth might enter, nor errour bee caſt out, let that bee
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:40364:35"/>obſerved, Hee now layes his ax to the root of the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance of the Miniſtery, that there may bee none to teach; quarrells at their maintenance, and fills the very calling with ſlander, begins by his inſtruments to talke of feare, hope, and reward, things which every religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly noble ſpirit, layeth as low as that whereon it treads, and looks a great deale higher unto that, Hee that winneth ſoules is wiſe, Hee that turneth many to righteouſneſſe ſhall ſhine as the Stars in the firmament: They that have this great worke in their hand, O that they would not wound one another, leſt God leave them at length to bee wounded one of another. Much adoe is made about having a Confeſſion, I think the Law of God well read and ſhortly gloſſed would ſerve, and none better; and ſuch a Creed, or Symbole of faith, I think were good as might bee definition-wiſe, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in nothing might bee deficient or redundant, onely ſuch things being therein contained as are neceſſary to bee known to ſalvation.</p>
               <p>Eightly, The Devil goeth about like a roaring Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, hee is never but either doing, or endeavouring to do ſome miſchiefe, privately or publiquely; Hee often transformes himſelfe into an Angel of light, and puts on ſhewes of holineſſe and ſanctitie, with which h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes ſo deceives good men, that unawares they lend him in his buſineſſe, an helping hand, Eminently God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly men doe not eſcape him without either crime or ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumnie if hee can help them to it, and hee is not wanting to ſeeke his advantages every where, to that purpoſe, his great engine that hee uſeth to doe miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe, which is the ſowing of ſtrifes, diſcords, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions, between men, and therefore we had need to bee prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for prevention.</p>
               <p>When the Senators conſpired againſt <hi>Caeſar</hi> to kill him in the Senate houſe, <hi>Antemidorus</hi> delivered him a paper en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring in, wherein all the Plot might have been diſcovered,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:40364:36"/>which <hi>Caeſar</hi> (then buſied with complements) wrapt u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> amongſt other Papers and Petitions, and thruſt into hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> pocket, and ſo not ſeeing the paper, went in, but loſt his life, and never came out again; what an opportunity was here loſt? Wee beſeech you in Chriſt his ſtead to be reconciled, let it not then bee ſaid of this and ſuch other meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages, who hath beleeved our report?</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:40364:36"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
